<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of the Reverend Mr. John Eliot, who was the first preacher of the Gospel to the Indians in America with an account of the wonderful success which the Gospel has had amongst the heathen in that part of the world, and of the many strange customs of the pagan Indians in New-England / written by Cotton Mather.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50138</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11795349</idno>
  <idno type="VID">49297</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240892745</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31238</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11795349</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1487:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of the Reverend Mr. John Eliot, who was the first preacher of the Gospel to the Indians in America with an account of the wonderful success which the Gospel has had amongst the heathen in that part of the world, and of the many strange customs of the pagan Indians in New-England / written by Cotton Mather.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition carefully corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Dunton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIV [1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Eliot, John, 1604-1690.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Massachuset Indians --  Missions.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE and DEATH Of the Reverend Mr. <hi>JOHN ELIOT,</hi> Who was the First PREACHER OF THE GOSPEL TO THE INDIANS in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With an Account of the Wonderful Success which the Gospel has had amongst the Heathen in that Part of the World: And of the many strange Customs of the Pagan <hi>Indians,</hi> In <hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Cotton Mather.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Religion stands on Tiptoe in our Land,</l>
               <l>Ready to pass to the <hi>American</hi> strand.—<bibl>
                     <hi>Herbert.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Third Edition</hi> carefully Corrected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Dunton,</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> MDCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable PHILIP Lord WHARTON, a no less Noble than Aged Patron of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Virtue; and a Favourite of that Great King, <hi>Whose Throne is in the Heavens, and whose King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Ruleth over all.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please Your Lordship,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF it be considered, that some <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and <hi>Apostolical</hi> Histories of the <hi>New Testament,</hi> were by the Direction of the Holy Spirit Himself, <hi>Dedicated</hi> unto a Person of Quality, and that the Noble Person Addressed with One such Dedication, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd it with Resentments that encouraged his dear <hi>Lucilias</hi> to make a <hi>Second;</hi> the World will be satisfied that I do a thing but Reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Agreeable, when, unto a Narrative of many <hi>Evangelical</hi> and <hi>Apostolical</hi> Affairs, I presume to prefix the Name of one so <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> for Love to God, as Your <hi>Lordship</hi> is known to be; and One upon this account only, an Ʋnmeet Subject for the Praises of the Obscure
<pb facs="tcp:49297:3"/> Pen which now writes that <hi>Quis Virtupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat?</hi> I do not, I dare not, so far intrude up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Your Honour, as to ask Your <hi>Patronage</hi> unto all the <hi>New English</hi> Principles and Practices which are found in the Character of our Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>ELIOT;</hi> for, as the Distance of a Thousand Leagues, has made it impossible for me to attend the <hi>(usual)</hi> Orders and Manners of asking first your Allowance for what I have open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Entituled you unto; so, the Renowned <hi>ELIOT</hi> is gone beyond any occasions for the greatest Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>Patronage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which has procured unto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, the Trouble of this <hi>Dedication,</hi> is, My Desire to give you the Picture of One <hi>Aged</hi> Saint, lately gone to that <hi>General Assembly,</hi> which the Eternal King of Heaven by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of your own <hi>Age in the way of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,</hi> does quickly Summon your Self un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. The profound Respect which our <hi>ELIOT</hi> had for your Honour, will doubtless be answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and requited with your own Value for the Memory of such a memorable <hi>Christian, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and <hi>Evangelist;</hi> inasmuch as, <hi>Your</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, like <hi>his,</hi> take not their Measures from these or those matters of <hi>Doubtful Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> but from such an universal <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Holiness,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> was an <hi>Instance</hi> of.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:3"/>
            <p>No Man ever complained of it, that in the Works of <hi>Chrysostom</hi> we find <hi>Seven</hi> Orations not far asunder, in Commendation of <hi>Paul;</hi> nor is it any fault that I have now written <hi>One</hi> in Commendation of a Man whom a <hi>Pauline</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit had made illustrious. In describing him, I have made but little Touches upon his Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and Family, because as the truly Great <hi>Basil</hi> excuses his Omission of those things, in his Oration upon <hi>Gordius</hi> the <hi>Martyr, Ecclesia haec tanquam supervacua dimittit.</hi> But I have related those things of him which cannot but create a good Esteem for him, in the breast of your Lordship, who are a Faithful and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Witness</hi> against those Distempers of the World, whereby (as the blessed <hi>Salvian</hi> lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) <hi>Cogimur esse Viles, ut Nobiles habea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur;</hi> and raise the sweetness of your Thoughts upon your Approaches, which may our God make both <hi>slow</hi> and <hi>sure,</hi> unto that State, wherein, <hi>The Least is Greater than this</hi> JOHN. But if I may more ingenuously Confess the whole <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Cause</hi> of this <hi>Dedication,</hi> I must own, <hi>'Tis to pay a part of a Debt;</hi> a <hi>Debt</hi> under which you have laid my Country, when you did with your own Honourable Hand, Present unto His Majesty the same Account which I have <hi>here</hi> again Published, <hi>Concerning the Success of the Gospel among the</hi> Indians <hi>in</hi> New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:4"/>
            <p>My Lord, in one <hi>ELIOT,</hi> You see what a <hi>People</hi> 'tis that you have counted worthy of your Notice; and what a <hi>People</hi> 'tis, that with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prayers bespeak the Mercies of Heaven for your Noble Family. Indeed, it is impossible that a Country so full as <hi>New-England</hi> is, of what is truly <hi>Primitive,</hi> should not be exposed unto the bitterest Enmity and Calumny of those that will strive to entangle the Church in a <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Ʋnreformedness, until our Jesus do shortly <hi>make them know, that He has loved</hi> what they have hated, maligned, persecuted. But if the God of <hi>New-England</hi> have inclined any <hi>Great Personage</hi> to Intercede or Interpose for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Ruines</hi> which ill men have designed for such a Country, or to procure for a People of an <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Complexion in Religion, the Ʋndisturbed Enjoyment and Exercise of <hi>that</hi> Religion: It is a thing that calls for our most sensible Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>It is an odd <hi>Superstition</hi> which the <hi>Indians</hi> of this Country have among them, that they count it (on the penalty of otherwise <hi>never prospering</hi> more) necessary for them, never to pass by the <hi>Graves</hi> of certain Famous Persons among them, without laying or leaving some Token of Regard thereupon. But we hope that all True <hi>Protestants</hi> will count it no more than what is <hi>equal</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> that the Land which has in it the <hi>Grave</hi> of such a Remarkable Preacher to the <hi>Indians</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49297:4"/> as our <hi>ELIOT,</hi> should be treated with such a <hi>Love,</hi> as a <hi>Jerusalem</hi> uses to find from them that are to <hi>prosper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ʋpon that score then, let My Lord accept a <hi>Present</hi> from, and for, a Remote corner in the <hi>New-World,</hi> where God is praised on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; a small <hi>Present</hi> made by the Hand of a Rude <hi>American,</hi> who has nothing to recommend him unto your Lordship, except this, that he is the Son of One whom you have admitted unto your Favours; and, That he is Ambitious to wear the Title of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordship's Most Humble and most Obedient Servant, <hi>COTTON MATHER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49297:5"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">'T</seg>Was a very surprizing as well as an undoubted Accident which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened within the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Millions yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, when certain Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds upon Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> following part of their Stragling Flock, at length came to a <hi>Valley,</hi> the prodigious Depths and Rocks whereof rendred it almost inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessible; in which there was a <hi>Cave</hi> of inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressible Sweetness, and in that Cave was a Sepulchre that had very difficult Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters upon it. The Patriarchs of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites</hi> thereabouts inhabiting, procured some Learned Persons to take Notice, and make Report of this Curiosity, who found the Inscription of the Grave-Stone to be in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language and Letter, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, the Servant of the Lord.</hi> The <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, were altogether by the Ears for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49297:6"/> the possession of this Rarity; but the <hi>Turks</hi> as quickly laid Claim unto it, and strongly guarded it. Nevertheless, the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits</hi> found a way by Tricks and Bribes to engage the <hi>Turkish</hi> Guards into a Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with them, for the Transporting of the inclosed and renowned Ashes into <hi>Europe;</hi> but when they opened the Grave, there was no Body, nor so much as a Relick there. While they were under the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of this Disappointment, a <hi>Turkish</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral came upon them, and cut them all to pieces; therewithal taking a course ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have that place visited any more. But the Scholars of the <hi>Orient</hi> presently made this a Theme, which they Talkt and Wrote much upon; and, <hi>whether this was the true Sepulchre of</hi> Moses, was a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion upon which many Books were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished. The World would now count me very absurd, if after this I should say, that I had found the Sepulchre of <hi>Moses</hi> in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica;</hi> but I have certainly here found <hi>Moses</hi> himself; we have had among us one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the <hi>Spirit and Power of a</hi> Moses; and it is not the Grave, but the Life of such a <hi>Moses,</hi> that we value our selves upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the owners of.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49297:6"/>
            <p>Having implored the Assistance and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of that God, whose Blessed Word has told us, <hi>The Righteous shall be had in everlasting remembrance;</hi> I am attempting to write the Life of a Righteous Person, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom all things, but the meanness of the Writer, invite the Reader to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing save what is truly extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. 'Tis the Life of one who has better and greater things to be affirmed of him, than could ever be reported concerning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of those famous Men, which have been celebrated by the Pens of a <hi>Plutarch,</hi> a <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> a <hi>Laertius,</hi> an <hi>Eunapius,</hi> or in any Pagan Histories. 'Tis the Life of one, whose Character might very agreeably be look'd for among the Collections of a <hi>Doratheus,</hi> or the Orations of a <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> or is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy at least of nothing less than the exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site Stile of a <hi>Melchior Adam</hi> to Eternize it. If it be, as it is, a true Assertion, <hi>That the least Exercise of true Faith or Love towards God in Christ, is a more glorious thing than all the Triumphs of a</hi> Caesar; there must be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing very considerable in the Life of one, who spent several Scores of years in such Exercises; and of one, in the mention of whose Atchievements we may also recount, that he fought the Devil in (once) his <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49297:7"/> Territories, till he had recovered no small Party of his old Subjects and Vassals out of his cruel Hands; it would be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable as unprofitable, for Posterity to bury the Memory of such a Person in the Dust of that Obscurity and Oblivion which has covered the Names of the <hi>Heroes</hi> who died before the Days of <hi>Agamemnon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preliminary">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49297:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PRAELIMINARY I. THE BIRTH, AGE, and FAMILY of Mr.</hi> ELIOT. 'Tis the Life of the Reverend <hi>John Eliot,</hi> which is to be now put into our Pages; a Life which commenced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year <hi>1604.</hi> And Expired in the Year <hi>1690.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE inspired <hi>Moses</hi> relating the Lives of the Ante-diluvian Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, in whom the Church of God, and Line of Christ was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, through the first Sixteen hundred Years of time, recites little but their Birth, and their Age, and their Death, and their Sons and Daughters. If those Articles would satisfy the Appetites and Enquiries
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49297:8"/> of such as come to Read the Life of our <hi>Eliot,</hi> we shall soon have dispatch'd the Work now upon our hands. The Age, with the Death of this Worthy man, has been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy terminated in the Ninetieth year of the present Century, and the Eighty sixth Year of his own Pilgrimage. And for his Birth, it was at a Town in <hi>England,</hi> the Name whereof I cannot presently recover; nor is it necessary for me to look back so far as the place of his Nativity, any more than 'tis for me to recite the Virtues of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, of which he said, <hi>Vix ea nostra voco.</hi> The <hi>Atlantick Ocean,</hi> like a River of <hi>Lethe,</hi> may easily cause us to forget many of the things that happened on the other side. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Nativity of such a Man were an Honour worthy the Contention of as many <hi>Places</hi> as laid their Claims unto the famous <hi>Homer's;</hi> but whatever <hi>Places</hi> may challenge a share in the Reputation of having En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd the <hi>first Breath</hi> of our <hi>Eliot,</hi> it is <hi>New-England</hi> that with most right can call him <hi>hers;</hi> his <hi>best Breath,</hi> and afterwards his <hi>last Breath,</hi> was here; and here 'twas that God bestow'd upon him <hi>Sons and Daughters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He came to <hi>New-England</hi> in the Month of <hi>November, A. D.</hi> 1631. among those Blessed old Planters, which laid the Foundations of a remarkable Country, devoted unto the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49297:8"/> Exercise of the Protestant Religion, in its purest and highest Reformation: He left behind him in <hi>England</hi> a vertuous young Gentlewoman, whom he had pursued and purposed a <hi>Marriage</hi> unto; and she coming hither the year following, that Marriage was Consummated in the Month of <hi>October, A. D.</hi> 1632.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Wife of his Youth</hi> lived with him until she became to him also the <hi>Staff of his Age;</hi> and she left him not until about three or four years before his own Departure to those Heavenly Regions, where they now together <hi>see Light.</hi> She was a Woman very Eminent both for <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Ʋseful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and she excelled most of the <hi>Daughters that have done vertuously.</hi> Her Name was <hi>Ann,</hi> and <hi>Gracious</hi> was her Nature. God made her a rich Blessing, not only to her <hi>Family,</hi> but also to her <hi>Neighbourhood;</hi> and when at last she died, I heard and saw her aged Husband, who else very rarely wept, yet now with Tears over the Coffin, before the good People, a vast confluence of which were come to her Funeral, say, <hi>Here lies my Dear, Faithful, Pious, Prudent, Prayerful Wife; I shall go to her, and she not return to me!</hi> My Reader will of his own accord excuse <hi>me,</hi> from bestowing any further <hi>Epitaphs</hi> upon that <hi>gracious</hi> Woman.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49297:9"/>
            <p>By <hi>her,</hi> did God give him six worthy Children; Children of a Character which may for ever stop the mouths of those <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian</hi> Blasphemers, who have set a false brand of Disaster and Infamy on the Off-spring of a <hi>Married Clergy.</hi> His First-born was a Daughter, born <hi>Sept.</hi> 17. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1633. This Gentlewoman is yet alive, and one well-approved for her Piety and Gravity. His next was a Son, born <hi>Aug.</hi> 31. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1636. He bore his Father's <hi>Name,</hi> and had his Father's <hi>Grace.</hi> He was a Person of notable Accomplishments, and a lively, zealous, acute Preacher, not only to the <hi>English,</hi> at <hi>New-Cambridge,</hi> but also to the <hi>Indians</hi> thereabout. He grew so fast, that he was found ripe for Heaven many years ago; and upon his Death-bed uttered such penetrating things as could proceed from none but one upon the Borders and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of Eternal Glory. 'Tis pity that so many of them are forgotten; but one of them, I think, we have cause to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: <hi>Well</hi> (said he) <hi>my dear Friends, there is a dark Day coming upon poor</hi> New-England; <hi>and in so dark a Day, I pray how will you provide for your own Security? My Counsel to you is, get an Interest in the Blessed Lord Jesus Christ; and that will carry you to the Worlds end.</hi> His Third was also a Son, born <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49297:9"/> 20. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1638. him he call'd <hi>Joseph,</hi> and made a <hi>Joseph</hi> of him: This Person is at this time a Pastor to the Church at <hi>Guilford,</hi> and one of great note, as well thro' the whole Country, as in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Colony of <hi>Connecticut,</hi> which God has made him considerable to. His Fourth was a <hi>Samuel,</hi> born <hi>June</hi> 22. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1641. who died, a most lovely young Man, Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for Learning and Goodness, a Fellow of the Colledge, and a Candidate of the Ministry. His Fifth was an <hi>Aaron,</hi> born <hi>Febr.</hi> 15. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1643. who tho he di'd very young, yet first manifested <hi>many good things towards the Lord God of Israel.</hi> His last was a <hi>Benjamin,</hi> born <hi>Jan.</hi> 29. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1646. Of all these Three it may be said, as it was of <hi>Haran, They died before their Father;</hi> but it may also be written over their Graves, <hi>All these died in Faith.</hi> By the pious Design of their Father, they were all Consecrated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Service of God, in the Ministry of the Gospel; but God saw meet rather to fetch them away, by a Death, which (therefore) I dare not call <hi>Pramature,</hi> to glorify him in another and better World. They all gave such Demonstrations of their Conversion to God, that the good old Man would sometimes comfortably say, <hi>I have had six Children, and I bless God for his free-grace,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49297:10"/> they are all either with Christ, or in Christ; and my mind is now at rest concerning them.</hi> And when some asked him, How he could bear the Death of such excellent Children? His humble Reply thereunto was this, <hi>My desire was, that they should have served God on Earth; but if God will chuse to have them rather serve him in Heaven, I have nothing to object against it, but his Will be done.</hi> His <hi>Benjamin</hi> was made the <hi>Son of his Right hand,</hi> for the Invitation of the good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Ruxbury</hi> placed him in the same Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit with his Father, where he was his As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistant for many years; there they had <hi>a Proof of him, that as a Son with his Father, he served with him in the Gospel.</hi> But his Fate was like that which the great <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> describes in his Discourse upon the Death of his honourable Brother, his aged Father being now alive and present: <hi>My Father, having laid up in a better World, a rich Inheritance for his Children, sent a Son of his before, to take possession of it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="preliminary">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49297:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PRAELIMINARY II.</hi> Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s early Conversion, sacred Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and just Removal into <hi>America.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BUT all that I have hitherto said, is no more than an entrance into the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our <hi>Eliot.</hi> Such an <hi>Enoch</hi> as he, must have something more than these things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of him; his <hi>Walk with God</hi> must be more largely laid before the World, as a thing that would bespeak us all to be <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers,</hi> no less than we shall be <hi>Admirers,</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>He had not passed many <hi>turns</hi> in the World, before he knew the meaning of a saving <hi>turn</hi> from the Vanities of an Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate State, unto God in Christ, by a true Repentance; he had the singular hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness and priviledge of an <hi>Early Conversion</hi> from the ways which <hi>Original Sin</hi> disposes all Men unto. One of the principal Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which the God of Heaven used in tinging, and filling the mind of this <hi>Chosen Vessel</hi> with good Principles, was that Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Thomas Hooker,</hi> whose Name in the Churches of the Lord Jesus, is <hi>As an Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment poured forth;</hi> even that <hi>Hooker,</hi> of whom Worthy Master <hi>Fuller</hi> could write:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49297:11"/> As <hi>Latimer</hi> would not stick to say, St. <hi>Bilney,</hi> so neither I to say, St. <hi>Hooker;</hi> that <hi>Hooker,</hi> who having <hi>Angled</hi> many scores of Souls into the Kingdom of Heaven, at last laid his Bones in our <hi>New-England;</hi> it was an Acquaintance with him, that contributed more than a little to the Accomplishment of our <hi>Elisha,</hi> for that Work unto which the most High designed him. His Liberal <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> having now the Addition of <hi>Religion</hi> to direct it, and improve it, it gave such a <hi>Biass</hi> to his young Soul, as quickly disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it self in very signal Instances. His first appearance in the World after his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation in the <hi>Ʋniversity</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> was in the too <hi>difficult,</hi> and <hi>unthankful,</hi> but very <hi>necessary</hi> Employment of a <hi>School-Master,</hi> which Employment he discharged with a good Fidelity. And as this <hi>first Essay</hi> of his Improvement was no more Disgrace unto him, than it was unto the famous <hi>Hierom, Whitaker, Vines,</hi> and others, that they thus began to be serviceable; so it rather pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared him for the further Service which his mind was now set upon. He was of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Mr. <hi>Thomas Wilson</hi>'s mind, that the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a Minister was the only one, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Man might be more serviceable to the Church of God, than in that of a <hi>School-Master.</hi> Wherefore having Dedicated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49297:11"/> unto God betimes, he could not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile himself to any lesser way of Serving his Creator and Redeemer, than by the Sacred Ministry of the Gospel; but, alas, where should he have Opportunities for the exercsing of it? It was now a time when some hundreds of those amiable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which had the Nick-name of <hi>Puritans</hi> put upon them, Transported themselves, with their whole Families and Interests, into the Desarts of <hi>America,</hi> that they might here peaceably erect <hi>Congregational Churches,</hi> and therein attend and maintain all the pure Institutions of the Lord Jesus Christ; having the encouragement of <hi>Royal Charters,</hi> that they should <hi>never</hi> have any Interruption in the Enjoyment of those <hi>precious and pleasant Things.</hi> Here was a prospect which quickly determined the devout Soul of our young <hi>Eliot,</hi> unto a remove into <hi>New-England,</hi> while it was yet a <hi>Land not sown;</hi> he quickly Listed himself among those Valiant Soldiers of the Lord Jesus, who cheerfully encountred first the Perils of the <hi>Atlantick Ocean,</hi> and then the Fatigues of the <hi>New-English Wilderness,</hi> that they might have an undisturbed Communion with him in his Appointments here. And thus did he betimes procure himself the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation of having afterwards, and for ever, a room in that remembrance of God, <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49297:12"/> thee, the Kindness of thy Youth, and the Love of thine Espousals, when thou wentest after me into the Wilderness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On his first arrival to <hi>New-England,</hi> he soon joyned himself unto the Church at <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston;</hi> 'twas <hi>Church-work</hi> that was his Errand hither. Mr. <hi>Wilson,</hi> the Pastor of that Church, was gone back into <hi>England,</hi> that he might perfect the Settlement of his Affairs; and in his Absence, young Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> was he that supplied his place. Upon the return of Mr. <hi>Wilson,</hi> that Church was intending to have made Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> his Collegue, and their Teacher; but it was thus diverted, Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> had engaged unto a select Number of his Pious and Christian Friends in <hi>England,</hi> that if they should come into these Parts before he should be in the Pastoral Care of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther People, he would give himself to <hi>Them,</hi> and be for <hi>Their</hi> Service. It happened, that these Friends transported themselves hither the year after him, and chose their Habitation at the Town which they called <hi>Roxbury.</hi> A Church being now gathered at this place, he was in a little while <hi>Ordained</hi> unto the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Ruling of that holy Society. So 'twas in the Orb of that Church that we had him as a <hi>Star fixed</hi> for very near Threescore years; it only remains that we now observe what was his <hi>Magnitude</hi> all this while, and how he performed his <hi>Revolution.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49297:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PART. I.</hi> Or, <hi>Eliot</hi> as a Christian.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE I.</hi> His Eminent Piety.</head>
               <p>SUch was the Piety of our <hi>Eliot,</hi> that like another <hi>Moses,</hi> he had upon his Face a continual <hi>Shine,</hi> arising from his uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Communion with the Father of Spirits. He was indeed a <hi>Man of Prayer,</hi> and might say after the Psalmist, <hi>I Prayer,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a manner made up of it. Could the Walls of his old Study speak, they would even ravish us with a Relation of the many hundred and thousand fervent Prayers which he there poured out before the Lord. He not only made it his daily practice to <hi>enter into that Closet, and shut his Door, and pray to his Father in secret,</hi> but he would not rarely set apart whole Days for Prayer with Fasting in secret places, before the God of Heaven. Prayer solemnized with Fasting was indeed so agreeable unto him, that I have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49297:13"/> thought he might justly inherit the Name of <hi>Johannes Jejunator,</hi> or <hi>John the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> which for the like reason was put upon one of the Renowned Ancients. Especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when there was any Remarkable Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty before him, he took this way to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter and overcome it; being of Dr. <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston</hi>'s mind, <hi>That when we would have any great things to be accomplished, the best Policy is to work by an Engine which the World sees nothing of.</hi> He could say as the Pious <hi>Robertson</hi> did upon his Death-bed, <hi>I thank God I have loved Fasting and Prayer with all my heart!</hi> If one would have known what that sacred thing, <hi>The Spirit of Prayer,</hi> intends, in him there might have been seen a most luculent and practical Exposition of it. He kept his heart in a frame for Prayer, with a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Constancy, and was continually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking all that were about him thereunto. When he heard any considerable News, his usual and speedy Reflection thereupon would be, <hi>Brethren, let us turn all this into Prayer;</hi> and he was perpetually jogging the Wheel of Prayer, both more privately in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and more publickly in the Churches of his Neighbourhood. When he came to an House that he was intimately acquainted with, he would often say, <hi>Come, let us not have a Visit without a Prayer; let us pray down
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49297:13"/> the Blessing of Heaven on your Family before we go.</hi> Especially when he came into a Society of Ministers, before he had sate long with them, they would look to hear him urging, <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the Lord Jesus takes much notice of what is done and said among his Ministers when they are together; come let us pray before we part.</hi> And hence also his whole Breath seemed in a sort made up of Ejaculatory Prayers; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny scores of which winged Messengers he dispatched away to Heaven upon pious Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands every day. By them he bespoke Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings upon almost every Person or Affair that he was concerned with; and he carried eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing to God with some pertinent <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sannah</hi>'s or <hi>Hallelujah</hi>'s over it. He was a mighty and an happy Man, that had his Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver full of these heavenly Arrows: And when he was never so straitly besieged by human Occurences, yet he fastned the wishes of his devout Soul unto them, and very dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terously shot them up to Heaven over the head of all.</p>
               <p>As he took thus delight in speaking to the Almighty God, no less did he in speaking of him; but in serious and savoury Discourses he still had his Tongue <hi>like the Pen of a ready Writer.</hi> The <hi>Jesuits</hi> once at <hi>Nola</hi> made a no less prophane than severe Order, <hi>That no man should speak of God at all;</hi> but this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49297:14"/> Person almost made it an Order wherever he came, <hi>to speak of nothing but God.</hi> He was indeed sufficiently pleasant and witty in Company, and he was affable and faceti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, rather than morose in Conversation; but he had a remarkable Gravity mixed with it, and a singular Skill of raising some Holy Observation out of whatever Matter of Discourse lay before him; nor would he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily dismiss any <hi>Theme</hi> without some gracious, divine, pithy Sentence thereupon. Doubtless he imposed it as a Law upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that he would leave something of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> with all that should come a near him; so that in all Places his Company was attended with Majesty and Reverence; and it was no sooner proper for him to speak, but, like <hi>Mary</hi>'s opened Box of Oyntment, he fill'd the whole Room with the Perfumes of the Graces in his Lips; and the Christian-hearers tasted a greater sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in his well-seasoned Speeches, than the Illustrious <hi>Homer</hi> ascrib'd unto the Orations of his <hi>Nestor, Whose Lip drop'd Language, than sweet Hony sweeter abundance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Conferences were like those which <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> affirms to have been common among the Saints in his Days, <hi>Ʋt qui sciret Dominum audire,</hi> as knowing that the Ear of God was open to them all; and he managed his Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49297:14"/> so as to manifest that he was bound Heaven-ward, in his whole Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He had a particular art at Spirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Earthly Objects, and raising of high Thoughts from very mean things. As once, going with some feebleness and weariness up the Hill on which his Meeting-house now stands, he said unto the Person that led him, <hi>This is very like the way to Heaven, 'tis up Hill! the Lord by his Grace fetch us up!</hi> and instant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spying a Bush near him, he as nimbly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>And truly there are Thorns and Briars in the way too!</hi> Which instance I would not have singled out from the many thousands of his Occasional Reflections, but only that I might suggest unto the good People of <hi>Rox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> something for them to think upon, when they are going up to the House of the Lord. It is enough, that as the Friend of the Famous <hi>Ʋrsin</hi> could profess that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver went unto him, without coming away, <hi>aut doctior aut melior,</hi> either the wiser or the better from him; so, 'tis an acknowledgment which more than one Friend of our <hi>Eliot</hi>'s has made concerning him, <hi>I was never with him, but I got, or might have got some good from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hearing from the Great God, was an Exercise of like satisfaction unto the Soul of this good Man, with speaking either to him, or of him. He was a mighty Student of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49297:15"/> Sacred Bible; and it was unto him as his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Food. He made the Bible his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, and his Councellor, and the Holy Lines of Scripture more Enamoured him, than the profane ones of <hi>Tully</hi> ever did the Famous <hi>Italian</hi> Cardinal. He would not, upon easy terms, have gone one day together without using a Portion of the Bible as an <hi>Antidote</hi> against the <hi>Infection</hi> of Temptation. And he would prescribe it unto others, with his <hi>probatum est</hi> upon it; as once particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a pious Woman, vexed with a wicked Husband, complaining to him, That bad Company was all the Day still infesting of her House, and what should she do? He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised her, <hi>Take the Holy Bible into your Hand, when the bad Company come, and you'll soon drive them out of the House;</hi> the Woman made the experiment, and thereby cleared her House from the haunts that had molested it. By the like way 'twas that he cleared his heart of what he was loth to have nesting there. Moreover, if ever any Man could, he might pretend unto that evidence of Uprightness, <hi>Lord, I have loved the habitation of thine House;</hi> for he not only gave something more than his presence there twice on the Lord's Days, and once a Fortnight besides on the Lectures, in his own Congregation; but he made his Weekly Visits unto the Lectures in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49297:15"/> Neighbouring Towns; how often was he seen at <hi>Boston, Charlstown, Cambridg, Dorche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> waiting upon the Word of God, in the recurring Opportunities, and counting a <hi>Day in the Courts of the Lord better than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand!</hi> It is hardly conceivable, how in the midst of so many Studies and Labours as he was at home engaged in, he could possibly repair to so many Lectures abroad; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he aimed not only at his own Edification, but at the Countenancing and Encouraging of the Lectures which he went unto. Thus he took heed that he might hear, and he took as much heed how he heard; he set himself as in the presence of the Eternal God, as the Great <hi>Constantine</hi> used of old, in the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies where he came, and said, <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will speak;</hi> he expressed a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent attention, by a watchful and wakeful Posture, and by turning to the Texts quoted by the Preacher; he expressed a suitable affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by feeding on what was delivered, and accompanying it with hands and eyes devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elevated; and they whose good hap 'twas to go home with him, were sure of having another Sermon by the way, until their very <hi>Hearts burned in them. Lactantius</hi> truly said, <hi>Non est vera Religio, quae cum Templo relinquitur;</hi> but our <hi>Eliot</hi> always carried much of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him from the House of God.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49297:16"/>
               <p>In a word, he was one who lived in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> while he was on <hi>Earth;</hi> and there is no more than pure Justice in our endeavours that he should live on <hi>Earth</hi> after he is in <hi>Heaven.</hi> We cannot say that we ever saw him walking any whither, but he was therein walking with God; wherever he sat, he had God by him, and it was in the everlasting Arms of God that he slept at Night. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughts he a little discovered his heavenly way of living, when walking one day in his Garden, he plucked up a Weed that he saw now and then growing there; at which a Friend presently said unto him, <hi>Sir, you tell us we must be Heavenly minded;</hi> but he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately repli'd, <hi>It is true; and this is no impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment unto that; for were I sure to go to Heaven to morrow, I would do what I do to day.</hi> From such a frame of Spirit it was that once in a Visit, finding a Merchant in his Counting-house, where he saw Books of Business only on his Table, but all his Books of Devotion on the Shelf, he gave this Advice unto him, <hi>Sir, Here's Earth on the Table, and Heaven on the Shelf; pray don't sit so much at the Table as altogether to forget the Shelf; let not Earth by any means thrust Heaven out of your mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed I cannot give a fuller Description of him, than what was in a Paraphrase that I have heard himself to make upon that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49297:16"/> Scripture, <hi>our Conversation is in Heaven.</hi> I writ from him as he uttered it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Behold, <hi>said he,</hi> the Ancient and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Character of a true Christian; 'tis that which <hi>Peter</hi> call <hi>Holiness in all manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation;</hi> you shall not find a Christian out of the way of Godly Conversation. For, first, a seventh part of our time is all spent in <hi>Heaven,</hi> when we are duly zealous for, and zealous on the Sabbath of God. Besides, God has written on the head of the Sabbath, <hi>Remember;</hi> which looks both forwards and backwards; and thus a good part of the Week will be spent in <hi>Sabbatizing.</hi> Well, but for the rest of our <hi>Time!</hi> why, we shall have that spent in <hi>Heaven,</hi> ere we have done. For, secondly, we have many Days for both <hi>Fasting</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> in our Pilgrimage; and here are so many <hi>Sabbaths</hi> more. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, thirdly, we have our <hi>Lectures</hi> every Week; and pious People wont miss them, if they can help it. Furthermore, fourthly, We have our <hi>private Meetings</hi> wherein we Pray, and Sing, and repeat Sermons, and confer together about the things of God; and being now come thus far, we are in <hi>Heaven</hi> almost every day. But a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fithly, We perform <hi>Family Duties</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day; We have our Morning and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Sacrifices, wherein having read the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49297:17"/> Scriptures to our Families, we call upon the Name of God, and ever now and then care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Catechise those that are under our Charge. Sixthly, We shall also have our daily Devotions in our Closets; wherein, unto Supplication before the Lord, we shall add some serious Meditation upon his Word; a <hi>David</hi> will be at this work no less than thrice a day. Seventhly, We have likewise many scores of Ejaculations in a day; and these we have, like <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> in whatever place we come into. Eighthly, We have our occasional Thoughts, and our occasional Talks upon Spiritual Matters; and we have our occasional Acts of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherein we do like the Inhabitants of <hi>Heaven</hi> every day. Ninthly, In our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, in our Civil Callings, we keep up heavenly Frames; we Buy, and Sell, and Toil, yea, we Eat and Drink, with some Eye both to the <hi>Command,</hi> and the <hi>Honour</hi> of God in all. Behold, I have not now left an inch of time to be Carnal; it is all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grossed for Heaven. And yet, lest here should not be enough, lastly, We have our Spiritual Warfare. We are always encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the Enemies of our Souls, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually raises our hearts unto our <hi>Helper</hi> and <hi>Leader</hi> in the <hi>Heavens.</hi> Let no Man say, <hi>'Tis impossible to live at this rate;</hi> for we have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49297:17"/> known some live thus, and others that have written of such a Life, have but spun a Web out of their own blessed experiences. <hi>New-England</hi> has Examples of this Life; tho, alas, 'tis to be lamented, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions of the World, in too many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, do becloud the beauty of an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Conversation. In fine, our Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lies in <hi>Heaven.</hi> In the morning, if we ask, <hi>Where am I to be to day?</hi> Our Souls must answer, <hi>In Heaven.</hi> In the Evening, if we ask, <hi>Where have I been to day?</hi> Our Souls may answer, <hi>In Heaven.</hi> If thou art a Believer, thou art no Stranger to Heaven while thou livest; and when thou diest, Heaven will be no strange Place to thee; no, thou hast been there a thousand times before.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In this Language have I heard him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press himself; and he did what he said, he was a <hi>Boniface,</hi> as well as a <hi>Benedict;</hi> and he was one of those, <hi>Qui faciendo docent, quae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienda docent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It might be said of him, as that Writer characterises <hi>Origen, Quemadmodum docuit, sic vixit &amp; quemadmodum vixit sic docuit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49297:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE II.</hi> His particular Care and Zeal about the <hi>Lords-Day.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis was the Piety, this the Holiness of our <hi>Eliot;</hi> but among the many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances in which his <hi>Holiness</hi> was remarkable, I must not omit his exact <hi>Remembrance of the Sabbath-day, to keep it holy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It has been truly and justly observed, That our whole Religion fares according to our Sabbaths; that poor Sabbaths make poor Christians; and that a Strictness in our Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths inspires a Vigour into all our other Duties. Our <hi>Eliot</hi> knew this, and it was a most Exemplary <hi>Zeal</hi> that he acknowledged the Sabbath of our Lord Jesus Christ withal. Had he been asked, <hi>Servasti Dominicum?</hi> He could have made a right Christian primitive answer thereunto. The Sun did not set, the Evening before the Sabbath, till he had begun his Preparation for it; and when the Lords-day came, you might have seen <hi>John in the Spirit</hi> every Week. Every day was a sort of Sabbath to him, but the Sabbath-day was a kind, a type, a taste of Heaven with him. He laboured, that he might on this high day have no Words or Thoughts but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49297:18"/> such as were agreeable thereunto; he then allow'd in himself no Actions, but those of a <hi>raised Soul.</hi> One should hear nothing dropping from his Lips on this day, but the Milk and Honey of the Country, in which there yet remains a Rest for the People of God; and if he beheld in any Person what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, whether Old or Young, any Profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this day, he would be sure to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow lively Rebukes upon it. And hence also unto the general Engagements of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, which 'twas his desire to bring the <hi>Indians</hi> into, he added a particular <hi>Article,</hi> wherein they bind themselves <hi>Meh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quontamvnat Sabbath, pahketeaunat tohsohke pomantamog, i. e.</hi> To remember the Sabbath-day, to keep it holy, as long as we live.</p>
               <p>The mention of this, gives me an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, not only to recommend our Depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Eliot,</hi> but also to Vindicate another great Man, unto the Churches of our Lord Jesus Christ. The Reverend and Renowned <hi>OWEN</hi> in his Elaborate Exercitations on the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> had let fall such a passage as this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I judge, That the Observation of the Lords-day is to be Commensurate unto the use of our natural strength on any other day, from Morning to Night. The Lords-day is to be see apart unto the ends of an holy Rest unto God, by every one, according as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49297:19"/> his natural strength will enable him to employ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his lawful occasions any other day of the Week.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This passage was subject to such a misun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, as that it gave some scandal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to several very Learned and Pious Men; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom our <hi>Eliot</hi> was one: whereupon with his usual Zeal, Gravity, and Sanctity, he wrote unto the Doctor his Opinion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about; who returned unto him an answer full of Respect, some part whereof I shall here transcribe.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>As to what concerns the <hi>Natural strength of Men (saith he),</hi> Either I was under some mistake in my Expression, or you seem to be so in your Apprehension. I never thought, and I hope I have not said, for I cannot find it, that the continuance of the Sabbath is to be Commensurate unto the natural strength of Man, but only that it is an allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mean of Mens continuance in Sabbath-Duties; which I suppose you will not deny, lest you should cast the Consciences of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors into inextricable Difficulties.</p>
                  <p>When first I engaged into that Work, I intended not to have spoken one word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the practical Observation of the Day; but only to have endeavoured the Revival of a Truth which at present is despised and contemned among us, and strenuously op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49297:19"/> by sundry Divines of the <hi>Ʋnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> who call the Doctrine of the Sabbath, <hi>Figmentum Anglicanum.</hi> Upon the desire of some Learned Men in these Parts, it was, that I undertook the Vindication of it. Having now discharged the Debt, which in this matter I owed unto the Truth and Church of God, tho not as I ought, yet with such a composition as I hope, thro' the Interposition of our Lord Jesus Christ, might find acceptance with God and his Saints, I suppose I shall not again engage on that Subject.</p>
                  <p>I suppose there is scarce any one alive in the World, who hath more <hi>Reproaches</hi> cast upon him than I have; tho hitherto God has been pleased in some measure to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port my Spirit under them. I still relieved my self by this, That my poor Endeavours have found acceptance with the <hi>Churches</hi> of Christ: But my Holy, Wise, and Gracious Father, sees it needful to try me in this matter also; and what I have received from you (which it may be contains not your sense alone) hath printed deeper, and left a greater impression upon my mind, than all the virulent Revilings, and false Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations I have met withal from my profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Adversaries. I do acknowledg unto you, that I have a dry and barren Spirit,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49297:20"/> and I do heartily beg your Prayers, that the Holy One would, notwithstanding all my sinful Provocations, water me from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; but that I should now be apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have given a Wound unto Holiness in the Churches, <hi>'tis one of the saddest Frowns in the Cloudy Brows of Divine Providence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Doctrine of the Sabbath, I have as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted, tho not as it should be done, yet as well as I could: The Observation of it in Holy Duties unto the utmost of the strength for them, which God should be pleased to give us, I have pleaded for; the necessity also of a serious Preparation for it in sundry previous Duties, I have declared. But now to meet with severe Expressions — it may be 'tis the Will of God, that vigour should hereby be given to my former Discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that there is a Call in it, to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease from these kinds of Labours.</p>
               </q>
               <p>I have transcribed the more of this Letter, because it not only discovers the concern which our <hi>Eliot</hi> had for the Sabbath of God, but also it may contribute unto the Worlds good Reception and Perusal of a <hi>Golden Book</hi> on that Subject, written by one of the most Eminent Persons which the <hi>English</hi> Nation has been adorned with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49297:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE III.</hi> His Exemplary Mortification.</head>
               <p>THus did <hi>Eliot</hi> endeavour to live unto God; but how much at the same time did he die unto all the World?</p>
               <p>'Twere impossible to finish the lively Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of this Pious and Holy <hi>Eliot,</hi> without some touches upon that Mortification which accompanied him all his days; for never did I see a Person more mortifi'd unto all the pleasures of this Life, or more unwilling to moult the Wings of an Heaven-born Soul, in the dirty Puddles of Carnal and Sensual Delights. We are all of us compounded of those two things, the Man, and the Beast; but so powerful was the Man, in this Holy Person, that it kept the Beast ever ti'd with a short Tedder, and suppressed the irregular Calcitrations of it. He became so nailed unto the Cross of the Lord Jesus Christ, that the Grandeurs of this World were unto him just what they would be to a dying Man; and he maintained an almost unparallel'd indifferency towards all the Pomps which Mankind is too generally flattered and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted with.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49297:21"/>
               <p>The Lust of the Flesh he could not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile himself to the least pampering or indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of; but he persecuted it with a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Antipathy; being upon higher Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples than <hi>Tully</hi> was acquainted withal, of his mind, <hi>Non est dignus nomine nominis, qui unum diem totum velit esse in isto genere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatis.</hi> The Sleep that he allowed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, cheated him not of his Morning-hours; but he reckoned the Morning no less a Friend unto the Graces, than unto the Muses. He would call upon Students, <hi>I pray look to it that you be Morning-Birds!</hi> And for many more than a score of years before he died, he removed his Lodging into his Study, on purpose that being there alone, he might enjoy his early Mornings, without giving the disturbance of the least noise to any of his Friends, whose Affections to him else might have been ready to have called, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, spare thy self.</hi> The Meat upon which he lived, was a <hi>Cibus simplex,</hi> an homely, but an wholesome Diet; rich Varieties, costly Viands, and poinant Sawces, came not upon his own Table; and when he found them on other Mens, he rarely tasted of them. One Dish, and a plain one, was his Dinner; and when invited unto a Feast, I have seen him sit magnifying of God for the Plenty which his People in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49297:21"/> were within a few years arisen to; but not more than a bit or two of all the Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties taken into his own Mouth all the while. And for a Supper, he had learned of his Loved and Blessed Patron, old Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> either wholly to omit it, or to make a small sup or two the utmost of it. The Drink which he still used, was very small; he cared not for Wines or Drams; and I believe he never once in all his Life knew what it was to feel so much as a noxious fume in his head from any of them; good clear Water was more precious, as well as more usual with him, than any of those Liquors with which Men do so frequently spoil their own Healths, while perhaps they drink those of other Men. When at a Strangers House in the Summer time, he has been entertained with a Glass, which they told him was <hi>of Water and Wine,</hi> he has with a complaisant Gravity replied unto this purpose, <hi>Wine, 'tis a noble, generous Liquor, and we should be bumbly thankful for it; but as I remember, Water was made before it!</hi> So abstemious was he; and he found, that <hi>Carere suavitaribus istit,</hi> his Abstinence had more sweetness in it, than any of the sweets which he abstain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from; and so willing he was to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers partake with him in that sweetness, that when he has thought the countenance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49297:22"/> of a Minister has look'd, as if he had made much of himself, he has gone to him with that Speech, <hi>Study Mortification, Brother! Study Mortification!</hi> And he made all his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses with a becoming Majesty.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lust of the Eye,</hi> was put out by him in such a manner, that it was in a manner all one with him to be Rich or Poor. It could not be said of him, That <hi>he sought great things for himself;</hi> but what Estate he became owner of, was from the Blessing of God upon the Husbandry and Industry of some in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, rather than from any endeavours of his own. Once when there stood several <hi>Kine</hi> of his own before his Door, his Wife to try him, asked him, <hi>Whose they were?</hi> And she found that he knew nothing of them. He could not endure to plunge himself into Secular Designs and Affairs, but accounted <hi>Sacerdos in foro</hi> as worthy of Castigation, as <hi>Mercator in Templo;</hi> he thought that Minister and Market-man were not <hi>Ʋnisons;</hi> and that the Earth was no place for <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Holy Mitre to be laid upon. It was the Usage of most Towns in the Country, to have an Annual Rate for the maintenance of the Ministry, adjusted commonly by the Select-men of the Towns; which tho it raised not any exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Salaries for the Ministers, who also seldom received all that the People had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49297:22"/> for; nevertheless in many places it prevented sore Temptations from befalling those that were labouring in the Word and Doctrine; who must else often have expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced the Truth of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Observation, <hi>Duriter profecto &amp; misere viverunt Evangelii Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistri, si ex Libera populi contributione essent su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stentandi.</hi> However, for his part, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded that what Stipend he had, should be raised by Contribution; and from the same Temper it was, that a few Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Dissolution, being left without an Assistant in his Ministry, he pressed his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to furnish themselves with another Pastor; and in his Application to them, he told them, <hi>'Tis possible you may think the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of maintaining two Ministers may be too heavy for you; but I'll deliver you from that fear; I do here give back my Salary to the Lord Jesus Christ; and now, Brethren, you may fix that upon any man that God shall make a Pastor for you.</hi> But his Church with an handsom reply, assured him, That they would count his very Presence worth a Salary, when he should be so super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuated as to do no further Service for them.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>Pride of Life,</hi> the Life of it was most Exemplarily extinguish'd in him. The Humility of his Heart made him <hi>Higher by the Head than the rest of the People.</hi> His Habit
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49297:23"/> and Spirit were both such as declared him to be among the Lowly, whom God has most Respect unto. His Apparel was without any Ornament, except that of Humility, which the Apostle Elegantly compares to a Knot of comely Ribbons, in the Text where he bids us to be Cloathed with it; any other flant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ribbons on those that came in his way, he would ingeniously animadvert upon; and seeing some Scholars once, he thought, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle too gaudy in their Cloaths, <hi>Humiliamini, Juvenes, Humiliamini,</hi> was his immediate Complement unto them. Had you seen him with his <hi>Leathern Girdle</hi> (for such a one he wore) <hi>about his Loins,</hi> you would almost have thought what <hi>Herod</hi> fear'd, <hi>That</hi> John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist <hi>was come to Life again.</hi> In short, he was in all regards, <hi>A Nazarite indeed;</hi> unless in this one, that long Hair was always very loathsome to him; he was an acute <hi>Ramist;</hi> but yet he professed himself a Lover of a <hi>Trichocomy.</hi> Doubtless, it may be lawful for us to accommodate the length of our Hair to the modest Customs which vary in the <hi>Churches of God:</hi> and it may be lawful for them that have not enough of their own Hair for their own Health, to supply themselves according to the sober Modes of the Places where they live. But the Apostle tells us, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teaches us, that if a Man have long Hair,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49297:23"/>
'tis a shame to him;</hi> where, by <hi>Nature</hi> can be meant, no other than, <hi>The difference of Sex;</hi> as the word else-where is used.</p>
               <p>Thus Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> thought, that for Men to wear their Hair with a luxurious, delicate, foeminine Prolixity; or for them to preserve no plain Distinction of their Sex, by the Hair of their Head and Face; and much more, for Men thus to disfigure themselves with Hair that is none of their own; and most of all, for Ministers of the Gospel to ruffle it in Excesses of this kind, may prove more than we are well aware displeasing to the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of God. I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that horrible Distemper prevailing in some <hi>European</hi> Countries, known by the Name of <hi>Plica Polonica,</hi> wherein the Hair of People matted into ugly and filthy Forms, like Snakes upon their Heads, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever cut off, presently fell Blind or Mad; I say, I know not whether this Disease was more odious in it self, than the sweeter, neater, but prolix Locks of many People were to our <hi>Eliot.</hi> He was indeed one <hi>priscis moribus,</hi> as well as <hi>Antiqua fine;</hi> and he might be allowed somewhat even of severity in this matter on that account.</p>
               <p>My Reader shall have a touch or two, from a Manuscript of his, which I have in my hands, against (as he calls it) <hi>The violent
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49297:24"/> and insuperable Lust of long Hair.</hi> He thus argues.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Tis a Sin for a Man to do that whereof he hath cause to be ashamed. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">But it is a shame for a Man to wear long Hair, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. Therefore 'tis a Sin.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> It was then so; but now 'tis a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion and Glory to do otherwise.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Ans.</hi> Nature is the same now as then, Unchangeable. It speaks as loud now as it did then; only <hi>our Ears are so covered with Locks, that we cannot hear it.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Again, Long Hair on the Head, and no Hair on the Face, is the Habit of a Woman, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. But it is a sinful <hi>Abomination</hi> for a Man to wear the Habit of a Woman. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.5.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Therefore 'tis a sinful Abomination for a Man to wear long Hair on his Head, and no Hair on his Face.</q>
               </p>
               <p>With these, and many other such Persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions did he endeavour to obviate the <hi>Luxury</hi> which he saw the Times degenerating apace into; and he added hereunto his own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as a continual and effectual Sermon against what he thought was to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49297:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE IV.</hi> His Exquisite Charity.</head>
               <p>HE that will write of <hi>Eliot,</hi> must write of Charity, or say nothing. His Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was a Star of the first Magnitude in the bright Constellation of his Virtues; and the Rays of it were wonderfully various and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensive.</p>
               <p>His Liberality to pious Uses, whether publick or private, went much beyond the Proportions of his little Estate in the World. Many hundreds of Pounds did he freely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow upon the Poor; and he would with a very forcible importunity press his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to joyn with him in such Beneficences. 'Twas a marvellous Alacrity with which he embraced all opportunities of Relieving any that were miserable: And the good People of <hi>Roxbury</hi> doubtless cannot remember (but the Righteous God will) how often, and with what Ardors, with what Arguments, he became a Beggar to them for Collections in their Assemblies, to support such needy Objects as had fallen under his Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Poor counted him their Father, and repaired still unto him, with a filial Confidence in their Necessities; and they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49297:25"/> were more than seven or eight, or indeed, than so many scores, who received their Portions of his Bounty. Like that Worthy and Famous <hi>English</hi> General, he could not persuade himself, <hi>That he had any thing but what he gave away;</hi> but he drove a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Trade at such Exercises at he thought would furnish him with Bills of Exchange, which he hoped after many days to find the comfort of; and yet after all, he would say, like one of the most Charitable Souls that ever lived in the World, <hi>That looking over his Accounts, he could no where find the God of Heaven charged a Debtor there.</hi> He did not put off his Charity, to be put in his Last Will, as many who therein shew that their Charity is against their will; but he was his own Administrator; he made his own Hands his Executors, and his own Eyes his Overseers. It has been Remark'd, That Liberal men are often Long-liv'd men; so do they after many days find the Bread with which they have been willing to keep other Men alive. The great Age of our <hi>Eliot</hi> was but agreeable to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark; and when his Age had unfitted him for almost all Employments, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved him of those Gifts and Parts which once he had been Accomplished with, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked, <hi>How he did?</hi> He would some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49297:25"/> answer, <hi>Alas, I have lost every thing; my Ʋnderstanding leaves me, my Memory fails me, my Ʋtterance fails me; but I thank God my Charity holds out still; I find that rather grows than fails!</hi> And I make no question, That at his Death, his happy Soul was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and welcomed into the Everlasting Habitations, by many scores got thither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, of such as his Charity had been liberal unto,</p>
               <p>But besides these more substantial Expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of his Charity, he made the Odours of that Grace yet more fragrant unto all that were about him, by that Pitifulness, and that P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acefulness, which rendred him yet further Amiable. If any of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood were in distress, he was like a <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther born for their Adversity,</hi> he would visit them, and comfort them with a most Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Sympathy; yea, 'tis not easy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how many whole days of Prayer with Fasting he has got his Neighbours to keep with him, on the behalf of those whose Calamities he found himself touched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. It was an extreme satisfaction to him, that his Wife had attained unto a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable skill in Physick and Chyrurgery, which enabled her to dispense many safe, good, and useful Medicines unto the Poor that had occasion for them, and some hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49297:26"/> of Sick, and Weak, and Maimed People owed praises to God for the Benefit which therein they freely received of her. The good Gentleman, her Husband, would still be casting Oyl into the Flame of that Charity, wherein she was of her own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord abundantly forward thus to be <hi>doing of good unto all;</hi> and he would urge her to be serviceable unto the worst Enemies that he had in the World. Never had any Man fewer Enemies than he! But once having delivered something in his Ministry which displeased one of his Hearers, the Man did passionately abuse him for it, and this both with Speeches and with Writings that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled him. Yet it happening not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that this man gave himself a very dangerous Wound; Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> immediately sends his Wife to cure him; who did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. When the man was well, he came to thank her; but she took no Rewards; and this good man made him stay and eat with him, taking no notice of all the Calumnies with which he had loaded him; but by this carriage he strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mollified and conquered the Stomach of his Reviler.</p>
               <p>He was also a great Enemy to all Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and would ring a loud <hi>Courfeu-Bell</hi> wherever he saw the Fires of Animosity.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49297:26"/> When he heard any Ministers complain, that such and such in their Flocks were too <hi>difficult</hi> for them, the strain of his Answer still was, <hi>Brother, Compass them!</hi> and <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, learn the meaning of those three little words, Bear, Forbear, Forgive.</hi> Yea, his inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Peace, indeed, sometimes almost made him to sacrifice <hi>Right</hi> it self. When there was laid before an Assembly of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, a bundle of Papers which contained certain Matters of Difference and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between some People, which our <hi>Eliot</hi> thought should rather unite, with an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty</hi> upon all their former Quarrels, he (with some imitation of what <hi>Constantine</hi> did upon the like occasion) hastily threw the Papers into the Fire before them all, and with a Zeal for Peace, as hot as that Fire, said immediately, <hi>Brethren, wonder not at what I have done, I did it on my Knees this Morning before I came among you.</hi> Such an excess (if it were one) flow'd from his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Inclinations, to be found among those Peace-makers, which by following the Example of that Man who is our Peace, come to be called, <hi>The Children of God.</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worthily might he be called an <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> as being all for Peace; and the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> gives unto the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of that Name, did belong unto our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49297:27"/>
                  <hi>Eliot;</hi> he was a <hi>most Blessed and a most Holy Man.</hi> He disliked all sorts of Bravery; but yet with an ingenious Note upon the <hi>Greek</hi> word in <hi>Col.</hi> 3.15. he propounded, <hi>That peace might brave it among us.</hi> In short, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he came, he was like another old <hi>John,</hi> with solemn and earnest persuasives to Love; and when he could say little else, he would give that Charge, <hi>My Children, love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, 'twas his Charity which dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him to continual Apprecations for, and Benedictions on those that he met withal; he had an heart full of good Wishes, and a mouth full of kind Blessings for them. And he often made his Expressions very wittily, agreeable to the Circumstances which he saw the Persons in. Sometimes when he came into a Family, he would call for all the young People in it, that so he might very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly lay his holy Hands upon every one of them, and bespeak the Mercies of Heaven for them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49297:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE V.</hi> Some special Attainments, that were the Effects of his Piety and Charity.</head>
               <p>BUT what was the Effect of this Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Piety and Charity in our <hi>Eliot?</hi> It will be no wonder, to my Reader, if I tell him, That this good man <hi>walked in the light of God's Countenance all the day long.</hi> I believe he had a continual assurance of the Divine Love, marvellously Sealing, Strengthning, and Refreshing of him, for many Lustres of Years hefore he dy'd; and for this cause the fear of Death was extirpated out of his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Soul, more than out of most men alive. Had our Blessed Jesus at any time sent his Waggons to fetch this old <hi>Jacob</hi> away, he would have gone without the least Reluctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Labouring once under a Fever and Ague, a Visitant asked him <hi>how he did?</hi> And he replied, <hi>Very well, but anon I expect a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxysm.</hi> Said the Visitant, <hi>Sir, fear not;</hi> but unto that he answered, <hi>Fear! No, no, I been't afraid, I thank God, I been't afraid to dye!</hi> Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would not have been any more to him, than Sleeping to a weary man.</p>
               <p>And another Excellency, which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied this Courage and Comfort in him,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49297:28"/> was, <hi>A wonderful resignation to the Will of God in all Events.</hi> There were sore Afflictions that sometimes befel him, especially when he followed some of his hopeful and worthy Sons, two or three desirable Preachers of the Gospel, to their Graves. But he sacrificed them, like another <hi>Abraham,</hi> with such a sacred indifferency, as made all the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to say, <hi>This could not be done without the Fear of God.</hi> Yea, he bore all his Trials with an admirable patience; and seemed loth to have any will of his own, that should not be wholly melted and moulded into the Will of his Heavenly Father. Once being in a Boat at Sea, a larger Vessel unhappily over-run, and over-set that little one, which had no small concerns, because <hi>Eliot</hi>'s, in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of it; immediately sunk without any expectation of ever going to Heaven any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way; and when he imagined that he had but one breath more to draw in the World, it was this, <hi>The Will of the Lord be done!</hi> But it was <hi>the will of the Lord</hi> that he should survive the danger, for he was rescu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the help that was then at hand; and he that had long been like <hi>Moses</hi> in every thing else, was now <hi>drawn out of the Waters:</hi> Which gives me opportunity to mention one Remarkable that had some relation hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. This accident happened in the time of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49297:28"/> our <hi>Indian</hi> Wars, when some furious <hi>English</hi> People that clamoured for the Extirpation of the Praying <hi>Indians,</hi> which were in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto us, as well as the <hi>Pagan Indians</hi> that were in Hostility against us, vented a very wicked Rage at our holy <hi>Eliot,</hi> because of his concernment for the <hi>Indians;</hi> and one profane Monster hearing how narrowly Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> escap'd from drowning, wish'd (as I am credibly informed) that this Man of God had been drowned. But within a few days, that woful man by a strange disaster was drowned in that very place, where Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> had received his Deliverance.</p>
               <p>There was indeed a certain health of Soul which he arrived unto; and he kept in a blessed measure clear of those Distempers which too often disorder the most of men. But the God of Heaven favoured him with something that was yet more extraordinary! By getting and keeping near to God, and by dwelling under the shadow of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he contracted a more exquisite s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nse of mind, than what is usual among other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of Christianity; he sometimes felt a lively touch of God upon his refined and exalted Spirit, which were not in any Paper of ours lawful or easy to be uttered; and he was admitted unto a singular Familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the <hi>Holy One of</hi> Israel. Henee 'twas,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49297:29"/> that as Bodies of a rare and fine Constitution will fore-bode the changes of the Weather; so the sublimed Soul of our <hi>Eliot</hi> often had strange fore-bodings of things that were to come. I have been astonished at some of his Predictions, that were both of a more personal, and of a more general Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and were follow'd with exact Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments. If he said of any Affair, <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bless it!</hi> it was a worse Omen to it than the most inauspicious Presages in the World; but sometimes, after he had been with God about a thing, he was able successfully to foretel, <hi>I have set a mark upon it, it will do well!</hi> I shall never forget, That when <hi>England</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lland</hi> were plunged into the unhappy War, which the more sensible Protestants every where had but sorrowful Apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of, our <hi>Eliot</hi> being in the height and heat of the War, privately asked, <hi>What News we might look for next?</hi> Answered, unto the surprize of the Enquirer, <hi>Our next News will be, a Peace between the two Protestant Nations; God knows, I pray for it every Day; and I am verily perswaded we shall hear of it speedily!</hi> and it came to pass accordingly.</p>
               <p>It is to be confessed, That the written Word of God is to be regarded as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and only Rule of our Lives; that in all Articles of Religion, if Men <hi>speak not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49297:29"/> to this word, there is no light in them;</hi> and that it is no warrantable or convenient thing for Christians to look for such Inspirations as directed the Prophets that were the Pen-men of the Scriptures. Nevertheless, there are some uncommon Instances of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Fruition, which in our days the Soveraign God here and there favours a good Man withal; and they are very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Persons, Persons well purifi'd from the <hi>Foecul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncies</hi> of Sensuality, and Persons better purged from the Leaven of Envy and Malice, and intollerable Pride, than usually those vain pretenders to Revelations, the <hi>Quakers</hi> are, that are made partakers of these Divine Dainties. Now such a one was our <hi>Eliot;</hi> and for this, <hi>worthy to be had in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Remembrance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would not be improper, under this File, to lodge the singular and surprizing Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of his Prayers! for they were such, that in our Distresses we still repair'd unto him, under that encouragement, <hi>He is a Prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live.</hi> I shall single out but one, from the many that might be mentioned: There was a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gentleman of <hi>Charlstown,</hi> one Mr. <hi>Foster,</hi> who, with his Son, was taken Captive by <hi>Turkish</hi> Enemies: Much Prayer was made, both privately and publickly, by the good
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49297:30"/> People here, for the Redemption of that Gentleman; but we were at last informed, that the Bloody Prince, in whose Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he was now a Slave, was resolved that in his Life-time no Prisoner should be releas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and so the distressed Friends of this Prisoner, now concluded, <hi>Our Hope is lost!</hi> Well, upon this, Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> in some of his next Prayers, before a very solemn Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, very broadly begg'd, <hi>Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, work for the Redemption of thy poor Servant</hi> Foster; <hi>and if the Prince which detains him will not, as they say, dismiss him as long as himself lives, Lord, we pray thee to kill that cruel Prince; kill him, and glorify thy self upon him.</hi> And now, behold the answer: The poor capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated Gentleman quickly returns to us that had been Mourning for him as a lost Man, and brings us News, that the Prince which had hitherto held him, was come to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely Death, by which means he was now set at Liberty. Thus we now know, <hi>That a Prophet has been among us!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49297:30"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PART II.</hi> Or, <hi>Eliot</hi> as a Minister.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE I.</hi> His Ministerial Accomplishments.</head>
               <p>THE Grace of God, which we have seen so Illustriously Endowing and Adorning of our <hi>Eliot,</hi> as well qualifi'd him for, as dispos'd him to the Employment wherein he spent about Six Decads of his Years; which was, <hi>The Service of the Lord Jesus Christ, in the Ministry of the Gospel.</hi> This was the Work to which he appli'd himself; and he undertook it, I believe, with as right Thoughts of it, and as good Ends in it, as ever any Man in our days was acted with. He look'd upon the Conduct of a Church, as a thing no less Dangerous than Important, and attended with so many Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, Temptations, and Humiliations, as that nothing but a Call from the Son of God, could have encouraged him unto the Susception of it. He saw that Flesh and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49297:31"/> Blood would find it no very pleasant thing to be oblig'd unto the over-sight of a number, that by a solemn Covenant should be listed among the Voluntiers of the Lord Jesus Christ; that it was no easy thing to feed the Souls of such a People, and of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the Neighbours, which were to be brought into the same Sheepfold with them; to bear their manners with all patience, not being by any of their Infirmities discouraged from Teaching of them, and from Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Praying over them; to value them highly as <hi>the Flock which God has purchased with his own Blood,</hi> notwithstanding all their miscarriages; and in all to examine the <hi>Rule of Scripture</hi> for the warrant of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever shall be done; and to remember the Day of Judgment, wherein an account must be given of all that has been done; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the mean time no expectation of the Riches and Grandeurs which accompany a worldly Domination. It was herewithal his Opinion, <hi>That</hi> (as the Great <hi>Owen</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses it) <hi>notwithstanding all the Countenance that is given to any Church by the Publick Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, yet whilst we are in this World, those who will faithfully discharge their Duty, as Ministers of the Gospel, shall have need to be prepared for Sufferings;</hi> and it was in a sense of these things that he gave himself up to the Sacred
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49297:31"/> Ministry. A stranger to Regeneration can be but poorly accomplished for such a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry; and however God may prosper the Sermons of such a Man for the advantage of his Church: However the building of the Ark may be help'd on by such Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as perish in the Flood, and the <hi>Tyrians</hi> may do some work about the Temple, who arrive to no Worship in the Inner-Courts thereof; and as <hi>Austin</hi> expressed it, a Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutter may convey Water into a Garden, without having himself any advantage of it; nevertheless, the unsanctifi'd Minister, how gifted, how able soever he may be, must have it still said unto him, <hi>Thou lackest one thing!</hi> and that <hi>one thing</hi> our <hi>Eliot</hi> had. But the <hi>one thing</hi> was not <hi>all!</hi> as, indeed, it would not have been <hi>enough.</hi> God furnished him with a good measure of Learning too, which made him capable to <hi>divide the Word aright.</hi> He was a most acute <hi>Grammarian;</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood very well the Languages which God first wrote his Holy Bible in. He had a sharp insight into all the other Liberal Arts, and made little Systems of them for the use of certain <hi>Indians,</hi> whose exacter Education he was desirous of. But, above all, he had a most Eminent Skill in <hi>Theology;</hi> and that which profane Scoffers reproach'd as the disgrace of the blessed <hi>Alting,</hi> all of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49297:32"/> whose Works always weigh down the purest Gold, was the honour of our <hi>Eliot,</hi> namely, to be <hi>Scripturarius Theologus,</hi> or, <hi>one mighty in the Word;</hi> which enabled him to convince Gainsayers, and on all occasions to show him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>a thorough Divine, and a Workman that needed not be ashamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In short, he came like another <hi>Bazaleel,</hi> or <hi>Aholiah,</hi> unto the Service of the Tabernacle. And from one particularity in that part of his Learning which lay in the Affairs of the Tabernacle, it was, that in a little Book of his, we have those Lines, which for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain cause I now transcribe: <hi>Oh that the Lord would put it</hi> (says he) <hi>into the heart of some of his Religious and Learned Servants, to take such pains about the</hi> Hebrew <hi>Language, as to fit it for universal use! Considering, that above all Languages spoken by the Lip of Man, it is most capable to be enlarged, and fitted to express all Things, and Motions, and Notions, that our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Intellect is capable of in this Mortal Life; considering also, that it is the Invention of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and what one is fitter to be the Ʋniversal Language, than that which it pleased our Lord Jesus to make use of, when he spake from Heaven unto</hi> Paul?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49297:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE II.</hi> His Family-Government.</head>
               <p>THE Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> reciting and requiring the Qualifications of a Gospel Minister, gives order, <hi>That he be the Husband of one Wife, and one that ruleth well his own house, having his Children in subjection with all gravity.</hi> It seems that a man's carriage in his own House is a part, or at least a sign of his due Deportment in the House of God; and then, I am sure, our <hi>Eliot</hi>'s was very Exemplary. That <hi>one Wife,</hi> which was given to him truly <hi>from the Lord,</hi> he loved, prized, cherished, with a Kindness that notably represented the Compassion which he (thereby) taught his Church to expect from the Lord Jesus Christ; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had lived with her for more than half an hundred years, he followed her to the Grave, with Lamentations beyond those which the <hi>Jews</hi> from the Figure of a Letter in the Text affirm, that <hi>Abraham</hi> deplored his aged <hi>Sarah</hi> with; her departure made a deeper Impression upon him, than what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny common Affliction could. His whole Conversation with her had that sweetness, and that gravity and modesty beautifying of it, that every one called them <hi>Zachary</hi> and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49297:33"/>
                  <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> His Family was a little <hi>Bethel,</hi> for the Worship of God constantly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly maintained in it; and unto the daily Prayers of the Family, his manner was to prefix the reading of the Scripture; which being done, 'twas also his manner to make his young People to chuse a certain passage in the Chapter, and give him some Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of their own upon it. By this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod he did mightily sharpen and improve, as well as try their Understandings, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make them <hi>wise unto Salvation.</hi> He was likewise very strict in the Education of his Children, and more careful to mend any Error in their Hearts and Lives, than he could have been to cure a blemish in their Bodies. No Exorbitances or Extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies could find a room under his Roof; nor was his House any other than a <hi>School of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> one might have there seen a perpetual mixture of a <hi>Spartan</hi> and a <hi>Christian</hi> Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Whatever decay there might be upon <hi>Family-Religion</hi> among us, as for our <hi>Eliot, we knew him, that he would command his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and his Houshold after him, that they should keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49297:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE III.</hi> His way of Preaching.</head>
               <p>SUch was he in his lesser Family! and in his greater Family he manifested still more of his regards to the Rule of a Gospel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry. To his Congregation, he was a Preacher that made it his care to <hi>give every one their Meat in due season.</hi> It was Food and not Froth, which in his Publick Sermons he entertained the Souls of his People with, he did not starve them with empty and windy Speculations, or with such things as <hi>Animum non dant, quia non habent.</hi> His way of Preaching was very plain, so that the very Lambs might wade into his Discourses on those Texts and Themes wherein Elephants might swim; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal it was very powerful, his Delivery was always very graceful and grateful; but when he was to use Reproofs and Warnings against any in, his Voice would rise into a warmth which had in it very much of Energy as well as Decency; he would brandish the Swords, and sound the Trumpets of God against all Vice, with a most penetrating Liveliness, and make his Pulpit another Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> for the flashes of Lightning therein displai'd against the breaches of the Law given upon that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49297:34"/>
                  <hi>burning Mountain.</hi> And, I observed, that there was usually a special fervour in the Rebukes which he bestow'd upon Carnality, a carnal Frame and Life in Professors of Religion; when he was to brand the Earthly-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Church-Members, and the Allowance and the Indulgence which they often gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themselves in sensual Delights, here he was a right <hi>Boanerges;</hi> he then spoke, as 'twas said one of the Ancients did, <hi>Quot verba tot Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina,</hi> as many Thunderbolts as Words.</p>
               <p>It was another property of his Preaching, that there was evermore much of Christ in it; and with <hi>Paul</hi> he could say, <hi>I determined to know nothing but Jesus Christ;</hi> having that Blessed Name in his Discourses, with a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency like that with which <hi>Paul</hi> mentions it in his <hi>Epistles.</hi> As 'twas noted of Dr. <hi>Bodly,</hi> that whatever Subject he were upon in the Application, still his Use of it would be <hi>to drive Men unto the Lord Jesus Christ;</hi> in like manner, the Lord Jesus Christ was the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone which gave a touch to all the Sermons of our <hi>Eliot;</hi> a glorious, precious, lovely <hi>Christ</hi> was the point of Heaven which they still verg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto: From this Inclination it was, that altho he printed several <hi>English</hi> Books before he dy'd, yet his Heart seemed not so much in any of them, as in that serious and savoury Book of his Intituled, <hi>The Harmony of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spels,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49297:34"/> in the Holy History of Jesus Christ.</hi> From hence also 'twas that he would give that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to young Preachers, <hi>Pray let there be much of Christ in your Ministry;</hi> and when he had heard a Sermon which had any special relish of a blessed Jesus in it, he would say thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>O blessed be God, that we have Christ so much, and so well preached in poor</hi> New-England!</p>
               <p>Moreover, he lik'd no Preaching but what had been well-studied for; and he would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much commend a Sermon which he could perceive had required some good <hi>Thinking</hi> and <hi>Reading</hi> in the Author of it. I have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent when he has unto a Preacher then just come home from the Assembly with him, thus expressed himself, <hi>Brother, there was Oyl requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Service of the Sanctuary; but it must be beaten Oyl; I praise God that I saw your Oyl so well beatenn to day; the Lord help us always by good study to beat our Oyl, that there may be no knots in our Sermons left undissolved, and that there may a clear light be thereby given in the House of God!</hi> And yet he likewise look'd for some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a Sermon beside and beyond the meer study of Man; he was for having the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> breathing in it, and with it; and he was for speaking those things from those Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, and with those Affections, which might compel the Hearer to say, <hi>The Spirit of God was here!</hi> I have heard him complain,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49297:35"/>
                  <hi>It is a sad thing when a Sermon shall have that one thing,</hi> the Spirit of God, <hi>wanting in it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE IV.</hi> His Cares about the Children of his People.</head>
               <p>BUT he remembred that he had Lambs in his Flock, and like another <hi>David</hi> he could not endure to see the Lion seize upon any of them. He always had a mighty concern upon his mind for little Children; 'twas an affectionate stroke in one of the little Papers which he published for them, <hi>Sure Christ is not willing to lose his Lambs;</hi> and I have cause to remember with what an hearty, fervent, zealous Application he address'd himself, when in the Name of the Neighbour Pastors and Churches he gave me <hi>the right hand of Fellowship at my Ordination,</hi> and said, <hi>Brother, Art thou a lover of the Lord Jesus Christ? Then, I pray, Feed his Lambs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One thing whereof he was very desirous for poor Children, was the Covenanting of them; he was very solicitous that the Lambs might pass under the Lord's Tything Rod, and be brought under <hi>the Bond of the Covenant.</hi> He very openly and earnestly maintained the Cause of <hi>Infant-Baptism,</hi> against a sort of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49297:35"/> Persons risen since the <hi>Reformation,</hi> (among which indeed there are many Godly Men, that were dear to the Soul of our <hi>Eliot</hi>) who forget that in the Gospel Church-State, as well as in the <hi>Jewish, the Promise is to Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and their Children;</hi> and are unwilling to reckon Children among the Disciples of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, or to grant, <hi>That of such is the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> or to know, That the most undoubted Records of Antiquity affirm <hi>Infant-Baptism</hi> to have been an usage in all the Primitive Churches: That even before the early days of <hi>Nazianzen, Chrysostom, Basil, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanasius, Epiphanius</hi> in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose, Jerom, Austin</hi> in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, all of which give glorious Test<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>monies for <hi>Infant-Baptism;</hi> even <hi>Cyprian,</hi> before these, assures us, that in his days there was no doubt of it; and <hi>Origen</hi> before him could say, <hi>'Twas from the Apostles that the Church took up the Baptism of Infants;</hi> and <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> before him could say, <hi>That Children should be Recipients of the Discipline of Christ;</hi> besides what plain evidence we have in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Justin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr;</hi> and that the very Arguments with which some of the Ancients did superstitiously ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise the delay of <hi>Baptism,</hi> do at the same time confess the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of <hi>Infants</hi> in it. Our <hi>Eliot</hi> could by no means look upon the <hi>Infants</hi> of Godly Men as unholy, and Unbelievers,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49297:36"/> and unfit Subjects to have upon them a <hi>Mark</hi> of Dedication to the Lord.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, when there was brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us a Book of pious Mr. <hi>Norcot</hi>'s, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by some became Disposed to, or Confirmed in a prejudice against <hi>Poedo-Baptism,</hi> it was not long before Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> published a little Answer thereunto; the first Lines whereof presently discover what a Temper he writ it with; says he, <hi>The Book speaks with the Voice of the Lamb, and I think the Author is a Godly, tho Erring Brother; but he acts the cause of a roaring Lion, who by all crafty ways seeketh to devour the poor Lambs of the Flock of Christ.</hi> And so he goes on to plead the Cause of them that cannot speak for themselves. No man could entertain a Person of a different per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion from himself, with more sweetness and kindness than he, when he saw <hi>Aliquid Christi,</hi> or the Fear of God prevailing in them; he could uphold a most intimate Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with such a man as Mr. <hi>Jessey,</hi> as long as he lived; and yet he knew how to be an <hi>Hammer</hi> upon their unhappy Errors.</p>
               <p>But having once Baptized the Children of his Covenanting Neighbours, he did not as too many Ministers do, think that he had now done with them. No, another thing wherein he was very laborious for poor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren was, the Catechising of them; he
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49297:36"/> kept up the great Ordinance of <hi>Catechising,</hi> both publickly and privately, and spent in it a world of time. About the end of the <hi>Second Century,</hi> before there had in the least begun to start up <hi>new Officers</hi> in the Church of God, we find that there were Persons cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto the Office of <hi>Publick Teaching,</hi> who were not Pastors, not Rulers, nor called unto the Administration of other Ordinances; those in the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> were of a special Remark and Renown for their Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties this way; and their Employment was to Explain and to Defend the Principles of the Christian Religion, unto all with whom they could be concerned. Here was the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techist, with reference unto whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle says, <hi>Let the Catechised communicate unto him in all good things.</hi> Now, tho some think, a Teacher, purely as such, hath no Right unto further Church-Administrations, any more than the Rabbies and Doctors among the <hi>Jews,</hi> had to <hi>offer Sacrifices in the Temple;</hi> yet he who is called to be a <hi>Teacher,</hi> may at the same time also be called to be an <hi>Elder;</hi> and being now a Teaching Elder, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes interested in the whole Government of the Church, he has the power of all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Administrations. 'Tis the latter and more compleat and perfect Character, which the Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> have stil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49297:37"/> in their Teachers; and such a Teaching-Elder did our <hi>Eliot</hi> remember himself to be. He thought himself under a particular Obligation to be that Officer, which the Apostle calls in 1 Cor. 4.15. <hi>An Instructor of the young;</hi> nor was he ashamed, any more than some of the worthiest Men among the Ancients were, to be called, A Catechist. He would observe upon <hi>John</hi> 21.15. That, <hi>the care of the Lambs is one third part of the charge over the Church of God.</hi> It would be incredible, if I should relate what pains he took to keep up the blessed Eccho's of Truth between himself, and the young Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Congregation; and what pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he used, in suiting of his Catechisms to the age and strength of his little Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumens. But one thing I must observe, which is, that altho there may be, (as one has computed) no less than five hundred Catechisms extant; yet Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the Travel of adding to their number, by composing of some further Catechisms, which were more particularly designed as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote for his own People, against the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of such Errors as might threaten any peculiar danger to them. And the effect and success of this Catechising, bore proportion to the indefatigable Industry with which he prosecuted it; it is a <hi>well-principled People</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:49297:37"/> that he has left behind him. As when certain Jesuits were sent among the <hi>Waldenses</hi> to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt their Children, they returned with much Disappointment and Confusion, because the Children of seven years old, were well-prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled enough to encounter the most Learned of them all; so, if any Seducers were let loose to wolve it among the good People of <hi>Rox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> I am confident, they would find as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Prey in that well-instructed Place, as in any part of all the Country; no Civil Penalties would signify so much to save any People from the Snares of busy Hereticks, as the unweared Catechizing of one <hi>Eliot</hi> has done to preserve his People from the gangreen of ill Opinions.</p>
               <p>There is a third Instance of his Regards to the welfare of the poor Children under his charge; and that is, his perpetual Resolution and Activity to support a good School in the Town that belong'd unto him. A Grammar-School he would always have upon the place whatever it cost him; and he importun'd all other Places to have the like. I can't forget the Ardour with which I once heard him pray in a Synod of these Churches, which met at <hi>Boston,</hi> to consider, <hi>How the miscarriages which were among us might be prevented;</hi> I say, with what fervor he uttered an Expression to this purpose; <hi>Lord, for Schools every where among
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49297:38"/> us! That our Schools may flourish! That every Member of this Assembly, may go home and procure a good School to be encouraged in the Town where he lives! that before we dye, we may be so happy as to see a good School encouraged in every Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Country.</hi> God so blessed his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, that <hi>Roxbury</hi> could not live quietly without a <hi>Free-School</hi> in the Town; and the issue of it has been one thing, which has made me almost put the Title of <hi>Schola Illustris</hi> up▪ that little Nursery; that is, That <hi>Roxbury</hi> has afforded more Scholars, first for the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and then for the Publick, than any Town of its bigness; or, if I mistake not, of twice its bigness in all <hi>New England.</hi> From the Spring of the School at <hi>Roxbury,</hi> there have run a large number of the <hi>Streams, which have made glad this whole City of God.</hi> I persuade my self, that the good People of <hi>Roxbury</hi> will for ever scorn to begrutch the Cost, or to permit the Death of a School which God has made such an Honour to them; and this the rather, because their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased <hi>Eliot</hi> has left them a fair part of his own Estate for the maintaining of the School in <hi>Roxbury;</hi> and I hope, or at least, I wish, that the Ministers of <hi>New-England</hi> may be as ungainsayably importunate with their People, as Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> was with his, for Schools, which may seasonably tinge the young Souls of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49297:38"/> Rising Generation. A want of Education for them, is the blackest and saddest of all the bad Omens that are upon us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>ARTICLE V.</hi> His Church-Discipline.</head>
               <p>IT yet more Endears unto us the Memory of our <hi>Eliot,</hi> that he was not only an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Minister, but also a true <hi>New-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> one; he was a Protestant, and a Puritan, and one very full of that Spirit which acted the first Planters of this Country, in their peaceable Secession from the unwarrantable things elsewhere impos'd upon their Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. The Judgment and Practice of one that readily underwent all the misery attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Infancy of this Plantation, for the sake of a true Church-order, is a thing which we young People should count worthy to be enquired after; and since we saw him so well <hi>behaving himself in the House of God,</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be worth while to know what he thought about the Frame, and Form, and Constitution of that blessed House.</p>
               <p>It was his as well as his Master, the great <hi>Ramus</hi>'s Principle, <hi>That in the Reformation of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49297:39"/> Churches to be now endeavoured, things ought to be reduced unto the Order wherein we find them at their Primitive, Original, Apostolical Institution.</hi> And in pursuance of this Principle, he just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly espoused that way of <hi>Church Government</hi> which we call the <hi>Congregational;</hi> he was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perswaded, that the <hi>Church-State</hi> which our Lord Christ hath instituted in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> is, <hi>In a Congregation or Society of Professed Believers, Agreeing and Assembling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, among themselves, with Officers of Divine Appointment, for the Celebration of Evangelical Ordinances, and their own mutual Edification:</hi> For he saw it must be a <hi>cruel hardship</hi> used upon the Scriptures, to make them so much as Lisp the least intimation of any other <hi>Church-State</hi> prescribed unto us; and he could assert, <hi>That no Approved Writers, for the space of two hundred years after Christ, make any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any other Original, Visible, Professing Church, but that only which is Congregational.</hi> He look'd upon the <hi>Congregational</hi> way as a Largess of Divine Bounty bestow'd by the Lord Jesus on his People, that follow'd him into this Wilderness, with a peculiar zeal for Communion with him, in his pure Worship here. He perceived in it a sweet sort of <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament,</hi> between <hi>Rigid Presbyterianism,</hi> and <hi>Levelling Brownism:</hi> So that on the one side, the Liberties of the People are not oppressed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49297:39"/> and overlaid; on the other side, the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Elders is not rendred insignificant, but a due <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llance</hi> is herein kept upon them both; and hence he closed with our <hi>platform of Church-Discipline,</hi> as being the nearest of what he had yet seen, to the <hi>Pattern in the Mount.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He could not comprehend, that this <hi>Church State</hi> can arise from any other Formal cause, but the Consent, Concurrence, Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of those concerned in it; he looked upon a Relation unto a Church, as not a Natural, or a Violent, but a Voluntary thing, and so that it is to be entred no otherwise, than by an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Covenant, or, as the Scripture speaks, by <hi>giving our selves first unto the Lord, and then one unto another.</hi> He could not think that Baptism alone was to be accounted the Cause, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Effect of Church-Membership; inas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as upon the Dissolution of the Church to which a man belongs, his Baptism would not become a Nullity: nor that meer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession would render men Members of this or that Church; for then it would be impossible to cut off a corrupt Member from that Body Politick: Nor that meer Cohabitation would make Church-Members; for then the vilest Infidels would be actually incorporated with us. And a Covenant, was all that he now saw remaining in the Inventory.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:49297:40"/>
               <p>But for the Subjects to be admitted by <hi>Churches</hi> unto all the Priviledges of this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship with them, he thought they ought to be such as a trying Charity, or a charitable Tryal, should pronounce <hi>Regenerate.</hi> He found the first <hi>Churches</hi> of the Gospel mentioned in the Scripture, to be Churches of Saints; and that the Apostles writing to them, still ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged them to be <hi>Holy Brethren,</hi> and such as were made <hi>meet for to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light;</hi> and that a main end of Church-Fellowship, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present unto the World, the Qualifications of those that shall <hi>Ascend into the Hill of the Lord, and Stand in his Holy Place for ever.</hi> He would therefore have, <hi>Bona Mens,</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Pectus,</hi> and <hi>Vita Innocens,</hi> required, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> tell us, they were in his Days, of all Communicants at the Table of the Lord; and with Holy <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> he would sooner have given his <hi>Heart-blood,</hi> than the <hi>Cup of the Lord,</hi> unto such as had not the hopeful Marks of our Lord's Disciples on them. The Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> still retain a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom which the great <hi>Justin Martry</hi> in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Century assures us to have been in the Primitive Churches of his Time; namely, <hi>To examine those they receive, not only about their Perswasion, but also whether they have attained unto a work of Grace upon their Souls.</hi> In the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49297:40"/> prosecution hereof, besides the Enquiries of the Elders into the Knowledge, and Belief, and Conversation of them that offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, unto Church fellowship, it is exprected, tho I hope not with any severity of impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that in the Addresses which they make to the Churches, they give some Written, if not Oral Account, of what impressions the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating Word of God has had upon their Souls. This was a Custom which this Holy man had a marvellous esteem and value for; and I have taken from his Mouth such as these Expressions very publickly delivered thereabouts.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">It is matter (said he) of great Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that we have Christ confessed in our Churches, by such as we receive to full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion there. They open the Works of Christ in their Hearts, and the Relation thereof is an eminent <hi>Confession</hi> of our Lord; experienced Saints can gather more than a little from it. It is indeed an Ordinance of wonderful benefit; the Lord planted many Vineyards in the first Settlement of this Country, and there were many Noble Vines in them; it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their Heavenly-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness which dispos'd them to this Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise; and by the upholding of it, the Churhes are still filled with Noble Vines; it mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintains purity of Churches. 'Tis the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49297:41"/> Duty of every Christian, <hi>With the Mouth Confession in made unto Salvation.</hi> As among the <hi>Jews,</hi> usually most men did once in their life Celebrate a <hi>Jubilee;</hi> thus this Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Christ, is methinks a sort of <hi>Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee;</hi> and every Good man among us, is at least once in his life call'd unto it. It is a thing that gives great Glory to the Lord Jesus Christ; and younger Converts are thereby exceedingly edify'd; and the Souls of Devout Christians are hereby ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much ingratiated one unto another. The Devil knows what he does, when he thrusts so hard to get this Custom out of our Churches. For my part, I would say in this case, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan; thou givest an horrible Offence unto the Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> Let us keep up this Ordinance with all Gentleness; and where we see the least spark of Grace held forth, let us prize it more than all the Wit in the World.</q>
               </p>
               <p>There were especially two things, which he was loth to see, and yet fear'd he saw, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Churches of <hi>New-England.</hi> One was, a thorough Establishment of Ruling-Elders in our Churches; which he thought sufficiently warranted by the Apostles men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Elders that Rule well, who yet Labour not in Word and Doctrine.</hi> He was very desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49297:41"/> to have Prudent and Gracious men set over our Churches, for the Assistance of their Pastors, in the Church-acts that concern the Admission and Exclusion of Members, and the Inspection of the Conversation led by the Communicants, and the Instruction of their several Families, and the Visitation of the Afflicted in the Flock over which they should preside. Such <hi>Helps in Government</hi> had he himself been blessed withal; the last of which was the well-deserving Elder <hi>Bowles;</hi> and of him, did this Good man, in a Speech to a <hi>Synod</hi> of all the Churches in this Colony, take occasion to say, <hi>There is my Brother</hi> Bowles, <hi>the Godly Elder of our Church at</hi> Rox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, <hi>God helps him to do great things among us!</hi> Had all our Pastors been so well accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated, it is possible there would be more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement given to such an Office as that of <hi>Ruling Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the mention of a Synod brings to mind another thing, which he was concerned, that we might never want; and that is, a frequent Repetition of needful Synods in our Churches. For tho he had a deep, and a due care to preserve the <hi>Rights of Particular Churches;</hi> yet he thought all the Churches of the Lord Jesus by their Union in what they profess, in what they intend, and in what they enjoy, so compacted into one
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49297:42"/> Body Mystical, as that all the several parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches every where should act with a regard unto the good of the whole, and and unto the common Advice and Counsel of the Neighbourhood; which cannot be done always by <hi>Letters Missive,</hi> like those that passed between <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> in the early days of Christianity; but it requires a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Churches in Synods, by their Delegates and Messengers. He did not count Churches to be so Independent, as that they can always discharge their whole Duty, and yet not act in a conjunction with Neighbour-Churches; nor would he be of any Church that will not acknowledge it self accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to rightly composed Synods, which may have occasion to enquire into the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of it; he saw the main Interest and Business of Churches might quickly come to be ueterly lost, if Synods were not often called for the Repairing of Inconveniences; and he was much in contriving for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and repeated meeting of such Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</p>
               <p>He wish'd for Councels to suppress all damnable Heresies or pernicious Opinions, that might ever arise among us; for Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels to extinguish all dangerous Divisions, and scandalous Contentions, which might ever begin to flame in our Borders; for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49297:42"/> Councels to rectify all Male-Administrations in the midst of us, or to recover any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches out of any Disorders which they may be plung'd into: For Councels to enquire into the Love, the Peace, the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness maintain'd by the several Churches. In fine, for Councels to send forth fit La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into those parts of our Lord's Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest, which are without the Gospel of God. He beheld an Apostolical Precept and Pattern for such Councels; and when such Councels convened in the Name of the Lord Jesus Christ, by the consent of several Churches concerned in mutual Communion, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, explained, recommended the Mind of God from his Word unto us, he reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Truth so delivered, challenged an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation from the particular Churches, with a very great Authority.</p>
               <p>He therefore printed an Ingenious little Book wearing this Title, <hi>The Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Gospel-Churches by the Ordinance of Councels, constituted in order according to the Scriptures, which may be a means of uniting those two holy and eminent Parties, the</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians <hi>and the</hi> Congregational. It is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Concession made by the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Jurieu,</hi> who is not reckoned a <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational</hi> man, in his <hi>Traite de l'Ʋnite de l'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glise, That the Apostolical Churches lived not in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49297:43"/> any Confederation for mutual Dependance. The grand Equipage of Metropolitans, of Primates, of Exarchs, of Patriarchs, was yet unknown; nor does it anymore appear to us, that the Churches then had their Provincial, National, and Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Synods; every Church was its own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, and independent on any other.</hi> But on the other side, out <hi>Eliot,</hi> who was no <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> conceived Synods to be the Institutions of our Lord Jesus Christ, the <hi>Apostolical Churches</hi> themselves acknowledging a stamp of Divine Right upon them.</p>
               <p>Such as these were the sentiments of our <hi>Eliot;</hi> and his deserved Reputation in the Churches of <hi>New-England,</hi> is that which has caused me to foresee some Advantage and Benefit arising unto the concerns of the Gospel, by so large a recitation as I have now made thereof.</p>
               <p>The Reader has now seen an able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the <hi>New-Testament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:49297:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PART III.</hi> Or, <hi>Eliot</hi> as an Evangelist.</head>
            <p>THE Titles of a <hi>Christian</hi> and of a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi> have rendred our <hi>Eliot</hi> considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but there is one memorable Title more, by which he has been signalized unto us. An honourable Person did once in Print put the Name of an <hi>Evangelist</hi> upon him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in a Letter of his to that Person, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards printed, his Expressions were, <hi>There is a Redundency where you put the Title of</hi> Evangelist <hi>upon me; I beseech you to suppress all such things; let us do, and speak, and carry all things with Humility; it is the Lord who hath done what is done; and it is most becoming the Spirit of Jesus Christ, to lift up him, and lay our selves low; I wish that word could be oblitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> My Reader sees what a Caution Mr. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liot</hi> long since entred against our giving him the Title of an <hi>Evangelist;</hi> but his Death has now made it safe, as his Life had long made it just, for us to acknowledge him with such a Title. I know not whether that of an <hi>Evangelist,</hi> or one separated for the Employment of Preaching the Gospel in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49297:44"/> such places where no Churches have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been gathered, be not an Office that should be continued in our days; but this I know, that our <hi>Eliot</hi> very notably did the Service and Business of such an Officer.</p>
            <p>The Natives of the Countrey now pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed by the <hi>New-Englanders,</hi> had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn and wretched <hi>Heathen</hi> ever since their first herding here; and tho we know not <hi>when</hi> or <hi>how</hi> those <hi>Indians</hi> first became Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this mighty Continent, yet we may guess, that probably the Devil decoy'd those miserable Salvages hither, in hopes that the Gospel of the Lord Jesus would never come here to destroy or disturb his <hi>Absolute Empire</hi> over them. But our <hi>Eliot</hi> was in such ill terms with the Devil, as to alarm him with sounding the Silver Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of Heaven in his Territories, and make some noble and zealous attempts towards outing him of his ancient Possessions here. Just before the first arrival of the <hi>English</hi> in these Parts, a prodigious Mortality had swept away vast Numbers of the poor <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians;</hi> and those <hi>Pagans</hi> who being told by a Shipwreck'd <hi>French</hi>-man, which dy'd in their hands, <hi>That God would shortly extirpate them, and introduce a more civil and worthy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into their place;</hi> blasphemously reply'd, <hi>That God could not kill them;</hi> were quickly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49297:44"/> kill'd with such a raging and wasting Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as left the very Earth covered with their Carkasses. Nevertheless, there were, I think, twenty several Nations (if I may call them so) of <hi>Indians</hi> upon that spot of Ground, which fell under the Influence of our Three <hi>Ʋnited Colonies;</hi> and our <hi>Eliot</hi> was willing to rescue as many of them as he could, from that old usurping Landlord of <hi>America,</hi> who is by the wrath of God, <hi>the Prince of this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot find that any, besides the Holy Spirit of God, first moved him to the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Work of Evangelizing these perishing <hi>Indians;</hi> 'twas that Holy Spirit which laid before his mind the <hi>Idea</hi> of that which is now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Seal of the <hi>Massachuset-Colony; A poor</hi> Indian, <hi>having a Label going from his Mouth, with a,</hi> COME OVER AND HELP US. It was the Spirit of our Lord Jesus Christ, which enkindled in him a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the dark, dying, damning Souls of these Natives, whom <hi>the God of this world had blinded,</hi> through all the by-past Ages. He was none of those that make <hi>the salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Heathen</hi> an Article of their <hi>Creed;</hi> but (setting aside the unrevealed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary steps which the <hi>Holy One of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> may take out of his usual Paths) he thought men to be lost, if our Gospel be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49297:45"/> hidden from them; and he was of the same Opinion with one of the Ancients, who said, <hi>Some have endeavoured to prove</hi> Plato <hi>a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, till they prove themselves little better than Heathen.</hi> It is indeed a Principle in the <hi>Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish Alcoran, That let a man's Religion be what it will, he shall be saved, if he conscientiously live up to the Rules of it:</hi> But our <hi>Eliot</hi> was no <hi>Mahometan,</hi> he could most heartily subscribe to that passage in the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">They are to be held accursed, who presume to say, that every man shall be saved by the Law or Sect which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth, so that he be diligent to frame his Life according to that Law and Light of Nature; for Holy Scripture do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h set out unto us, only the Name of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sus Christ, whereby men must be saved.</q> And it astonished him to see many dissembling Subscribers of those Articles, while they have grown up to such a Frenzy, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peremptorily all Church-state, and all Salvation to all that are not under <hi>Diocesan Bishops;</hi> yet at the same time to grant that the <hi>Heathen</hi> might be saved without the Knowledge of the Lord Jesus Christ. No, It very powerfully moved his holy Bowels, to hear the Thunderclaps of that Impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over the Heads of our naked <hi>Indians, Pour out thy Fury upon the Heathen that know
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49297:45"/> thee not;</hi> and thought he, <hi>What shall I do to rescue these Heathen from that all-devouring Fury?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when this Charitable pity had once begun to flame, there was a concurrence of many things to cast Oyl into it. All the good men in the Country were glad of his engagement in such an undertaking; the Ministers especially encouraged him, and those in the Neighbourhood kindly sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd his place, and perform'd his work, in part, for him at <hi>Roxbury,</hi> while he was abroad labouring among them that were without. Hereunto he was further awakened by those Expressions in the Royal Charter, in the assurance and protection whereof this Wilderness was first peopled, namely, <hi>To win and incite the Natives of that Country to the knowledge and obedience of the only true God and Saviour of Mankind, and the Christian Faith, in our Royal Intention; and the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers free profession is the principal end of the Plantation.</hi> And the remarkable Zeal of the <hi>Romish</hi> Missionaries <hi>compassing Sea and Land that they might make Proselytes,</hi> made his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Soul think of it with a further dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that we should come any whit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in our care to Evangelize the <hi>Indians,</hi> whom we dwelt among. Lastly, When he had well begun this Evangelical Business,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49297:46"/> the good God, in an answer to his Prayers, mercifully stirred up a liberal Contribution among the godly people in <hi>England</hi> for the promoting of it; by means whereof, a considerable Estate and Income was at length entrusted in the hands of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Corporation, by whom 'tis to this day very carefully employed in the Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stian Service, which it was designed for. And then, in short, inasmuch as our Lord Jesus had bestowed on us, our <hi>Eliot</hi> was gratefully and generously desirous to obtain for him, <hi>The Heathen for an Inheritance, and the utmost parts of the earth for a possession.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Exemplary Charity of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent person in this important Affair, will not be seen in its due lustre, unless we make some Reflections upon several Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances which he beheld these forlorn <hi>Indians</hi> in. Know then, that these doleful Creatures are the veriest <hi>Ruines of Mankind,</hi> which are to be found any where upon the face of the Earth. No such Estates are to be expected among them, as have been the Baits which the pretended Converters in other Countries have snapped at. One might see among them, what an hard Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster the Devil is to the most devoted of his Vassals! These abject Creatures live in a Country full of Mines; we have already
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49297:46"/> made entrance upon our Iron; and in the very surface of the ground among us there li s Copper enough to supply all this World; besides other Mines hereafter to be exposed; but our shiftless <hi>Indians</hi> were never Owners of so much as a Knife, till we came among them; their name for an <hi>English-man,</hi> was a <hi>Knife-man;</hi> Stone was instead of Metal for their Tools; and for their Coins, they have only little Beads with Holes in them to string them upon a Bracelet, whereof some are white; and of these there go six for a penny; some are black or blew; and of these, go three for a penny; this <hi>Wampam,</hi> as they call it, is made of the Shell-fish, which lies upon th Sea-coast continually.</p>
            <p>They live in a Country, where we now have all the conveniences of humane life: bur as for them, their Housing is nothing but a few Matts ty'd about Poles fastened in the Earth, where a good Fire is their Bed-clothes in the coldest Seasons; their Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is but a skin of a Beast, covering their Hind-parts, their Fore-parts having but a little Apron where nature calls for secrecy; their Diet has not a greater dainty than their <hi>Nokehick,</hi> that is, a spoonful of their parch'd meal, with a spoonful of water, which will strengthen tnem to travel a day toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49297:47"/> except we should mention the Flesh of Deers, Bears, Moose, Rackoons, and the like; which they have when they can catch them; as also a little Fish, which if they would preserve, 'twas by drying, not by salting; for they had not a grain of Salt in the World, I think, till we bestow'd it on them. Their Physick is, excepting a few odd Specificks, which some of them encounter certain cases with, nothing hardly, but an Hot-house, or a <hi>Powaw,</hi> Their Hot-house is a little Cave, about eight foot over; where, after they have terribly heated it, a crew of them go sit and sweat, and smoke for an hour together, and then immediately run into some very cold adjacent brook, without the least mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to them; 'tis this way they recover themselves from some Diseases, particularly from the <hi>French;</hi> but in most of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Distempers, 'tis a <hi>Powaw</hi> that must be sent for; that is, a Priest, who has more Familiarity with Satan than his Neighbours; this Conjurer comes and roars, and howls, and uses Magical Ceremonies over the Sick man, and will be well paid for it when he has done; if this don't effect the cure, the <hi>Man's Time is come, and there's an end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They live in a Country full of the best Ship-Timber under Heaven: but never saw
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49297:47"/> a Ship till some came from <hi>Europe</hi> hither; and then they were scar'd out of their wits, to see the Monster come sailing in, and spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fire with a mighty noise out of her floating side; they cross the water in <hi>Canoo's,</hi> made sometimes of Trees which they burn and hew till they have hallow'd them; and sometimes of Barks, which they stitch into a light sort of a Vessel, to be easily carried over land; if they are over-set, it is but a little padling like a Dog, and they are soon where they were.</p>
            <p>Their way of living is infinitely barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: the men are most abominably sloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; making their poor <hi>Squaws,</hi> or Wives, to plant, and dress, and barn, and beat their Corn, and build their <hi>Wigwams</hi> for them; which, perhaps, may be the reason of their extraordinary ease in Childbirth. In the mean time, their chief employment, when they'l condescend unto any, is that of Hunting, wherein they'l go out some scores, if not hundreds of them in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, driving all before them.</p>
            <p>They continue in a place till they have burnt up all the Wood thereabouts, and then they pluck up Stakes, to follow the Wood which they cannot fetch home unto themselves; hence when they enquire about the <hi>English, Why come they hither?</hi> they have
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49297:48"/> themselves very learnedly determined the case, <hi>'Twas because we wanted Firing.</hi> No Arts are understood among them, unless just so far as to maintain their Bruitish Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is little more than is to be found among the very <hi>Bevers</hi> upon our Streams.</p>
            <p>Their division of Time is by Sleeps, and Moons, and Winters; and by lodging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad they have somewhat observed the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Stars; among which it has been surprising unto me to find, that they have always call'd <hi>Charles's Wain</hi> by the name of <hi>Paukunnawaw,</hi> or <hi>The Bear,</hi> which is the name whereby <hi>Europeans</hi> also have distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished it. Moreover, they have little, if any Traditions among them worthy of our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice; and Reading and Writing is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unknown to them, though there is a Rock or two in the Countrey that has unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Characters engrav'd upon it. All the Religion they have, amounts unto thus much: They believe that there are many Gods, who made and own the several Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World; of which a certain Great God in the South-west Regions of Heaven, bears the greatest Figure. They believe, that every remarkable Creature has a peculiar God within it, or about it: There is with them, a Sun-God, a Moon-God,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49297:48"/> and the like; and they cannot conceive but that the Fire must be a kind of a God, inasmuch as a Spark of it will soon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce very strange effects. They believe that when any good or ill happens to them, there is the favour or the anger of a God expressed in it; and hence, as in a time of Calamity, they keep a Dance, or a day of extravagant ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Devotions to their God; so in a time of Prosperity they likewise have a Feast, wherein they also make presents one unto another. Finally, They believe, that their chief God <hi>Kautantowit,</hi> made a Man and Woman of a Stone; which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dislike, he broke to pieces, and made another Man and Womon of a Tree, which were the Fountains of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and, that we all have in us im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, which, if we were godly, shall go to a splendid entertainment with <hi>Kautantowit;</hi> but otherwise, must wander about in a restless horror for ever. But if you say to them any thing of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, they will reply upon you, <hi>I shall never believe it.</hi> And when they have any weighty undertaking before them, 'tis an usual thing for them to have their Assemblies, wherein after the usage
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49297:49"/> of some Diabolical Rites, a Devil appears unto them, to inform them, and advise them about their circumstances; and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there are odd Events of their making these Applications to the Devil. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, 'tis particularly affirmed, That the <hi>Indians</hi> in their Wars with us, finding a sore inconvenience by our Dogs, which would make a sad yelling if in the night they scented the approaches of them, they sacrificed a Dog to the Devil; after which no <hi>English</hi> Dog would bark at an <hi>Indian</hi> for divers months ensuing. This was the miserable people which our <hi>Eliot</hi> propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto himself the saving of! And he had a double work incumbent on him; he was to make Men of them, ere he could hope to see them Saints; they must be civilized ere they could be Christianized; he could not, as <hi>Gregory</hi> once of our Nation, see any thing Angelical to bespeak his Labours for their eternal Welfare; all among them was Diabolical. To think on raising a Number of these hideous Creatures unto the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of our holy Religion, must argue more than common or little Sentiments in the Undertaker; but the Faith of an <hi>Eliot</hi> could encounter it!</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49297:49"/>
            <p>I confess there was one, I cannot call it so much guess as wish, wherein he was willing a little to indulge himself; and that was, <hi>That our</hi> Indians <hi>are the posterity of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and rejected</hi> Israelites, concerning whom our God has promised <hi>that they shall yet be saved by the Deliverer, coming to turn away ungodliness from them.</hi> He saw the <hi>Indians</hi> using many Parables in their Discourses; much given to the anointing of their Heads; much delighted in Dancing, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially after Victories; computing their Times by Nights and Months; giving Dowries for Wives, and causing their Women to <hi>dwell by themselves</hi> at certain seasons, for secret causes; and accustom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves to grievous Mournings and Yellowings for the Dead; all which were usual things among the <hi>Israelites.</hi> They have too a great unkindness for our Swine; but I suppose that is because our Hogs devour the <hi>Clams,</hi> which are a Dainty with them. He also saw some Learned Men looking for the lost <hi>Israelites</hi> among the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> and counting that they had thorow good reasons for doing so. And a few small Arguments, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but Conjectures, meeting with a favourable disposition in the hearer, will carry some conviction with them; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49297:50"/> if a Report of a <hi>Menasseh ben Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> be to back them. He saw likewise the Judgments threatned unto the <hi>Israel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> of Old, Strangely fulfilled upon our <hi>Indians;</hi> particularly that, <hi>Ye shall eat the flesh of your Sons,</hi> which is done with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite Cruelties upon the Prisoners that they take from one another in their Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels. Moreover, 'tis a Prophecy in <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.68. <hi>The Lord shall bring thee into Egypt again with ships, by the way whereof I spake unto thee, Thou shalt see it no more again: And there shall ye be sold unto your Enemies, and no man shall buy you.</hi> This did our <hi>Eliot</hi> imagine accomplished, when the Captives taken by us in our late Wars upon them, were sent to be sold in the Coasts, lying not very remote from <hi>Egypt</hi> on the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranian</hi> Sea; and scarce any Chapmen would offer to take them off, being upon such as these accounts not unwilling, if it were possible, to have the <hi>Indians</hi> found <hi>Israelites,</hi> they were, you may be sure, not a whit the less <hi>beloved for their</hi> (sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed) <hi>Fathers sake;</hi> and the Fatigues of his Travels went on the more cheerfully, or at least, the more hopefully, because of such possibilities.</p>
            <p>The first step which he judged necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry now to be taken by him, was to learn
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49297:50"/> the <hi>Indian</hi> Language, for he saw them so stupid and sensless, that they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do so much as enquire after the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Strangers now come into their Country, much less would they so far imitate us as to leave off their beastly way of living, that they might be partakers of any Spiritual advantage by us, unless we could first address them in a Language of their own. Behold, new difficulties to be surmounted by our indefatigable <hi>Eliot!</hi> he hires a Native to teach him this Exotick Language, and with a laborious Care and Skill reduces it into a <hi>Grammar,</hi> which afterwards he published. There is a Letter or two of our Alphabet which the <hi>Indians</hi> never had in theirs; tho' there were enough of the Dog in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, there can scarce be found an <hi>R</hi> in their Language, save that the <hi>Indians</hi> to the Northward, who have a peculiar Dialect, pronounce an <hi>R</hi> where an <hi>N</hi> is pronounced by our <hi>Indians;</hi> but if their Alphabet be short, I am sure the words composed of it are long enough to tire the Patience of any Scholar in the World, they are <hi>Sesquipedalia Verba,</hi> which their <hi>Linguo</hi> is composed of; one would think they have been growing ever since <hi>Babel,</hi> unto the dimensions to which they are now
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49297:51"/> extended. For instance, if my Reader will count how many Letters there are in this one word, <hi>Nummatchekodtantamoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onganunnonash,</hi> when he has done, for his reward I'll tell him, it signifies no more in <hi>English</hi> than, <hi>our Lusts;</hi> and if I were to translate, <hi>our Loves,</hi> it must be nothing shorter than <hi>Noowomantammooonkanunon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nash.</hi> Nor do we find in all this Language the least Affinity to, or Derivation from any <hi>Europaean</hi> Speech that we are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with. I know not what thoughts it will produce in my Reader, when I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him, that once finding that the <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> in a possessed young Woman, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have given the World some account, understood the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Languages, my Curiosity led me to make trial of this <hi>Indian</hi> Language, and the <hi>Daemons</hi> did seem as if they did not understand it: This tedious Language our <hi>Eliot</hi> quickly became a Master of; he employed a pregnant and witty <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who also spoke <hi>English</hi> well, for his assistance in it; and compiling some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses by his help, he would single out a <hi>Word,</hi> a <hi>Noun,</hi> a <hi>Verb,</hi> and pursue it through all its variations: Having finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>Grammar,</hi> at the close he writes, <hi>Prayers and Pains, through Faith in Christ
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49297:51"/> Jesus, will do any thing!</hi> And being by his Prayers and Pains thus furnished, he set himself in the Year 1646 to preaeh the Gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong these desolate outcasts.</p>
            <p>¶ It remains that I lay before the World, the remarkable Conduct and Success of this Famous Man in his great Affair; and I shall endeavour to do it, by Englishing and Reprinting a Letter, sent a while since by my Father, unto his Learned and Renown'd Correspondent, the Venerable Dr. <hi>Luesden</hi> at <hi>Utrecht;</hi> which Letter has already been published, if I mistake not, in four or five divers Languages. I find it particularly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by the most excellent <hi>Jurieu,</hi> at the end of a <hi>Pastoral Letter;</hi> and this Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then worthily made upon it, <hi>Cette Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre doit opporter une tres grande Consolation, a toutes les bonnes ames, qui sont alterees de Justice, &amp; qui sont enflammees du zele de la glorie de Dieu.</hi> I therefore perswade my self, that the Republication of it will not be ungrateful unto many good Souls in our Nation, who have a due thirst and zeal for such things as are mention'd in it; and when that is done, I shall presume to make some <hi>Annotations</hi> for the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of sundry memorable things therein pointed at.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:49297:52"/>
               <head>A LETTER concerning the Success of the Gospel amongst the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </head>
               <byline>Written by Mr. <hi>Increase Mather,</hi> Minister of the Word of God at <hi>Boston,</hi> and Rector of the Colledge at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> to Doctor <hi>John Leusden,</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Professor in the University of <hi>Utrecht.</hi>
               </byline>
               <head>Translated out of <hi>Latin</hi> into <hi>English.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Worthy and much honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Letters were very grateful to to me, <hi>(a)</hi> by which I understand that you and others in your famous Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of <hi>Utrecht</hi> desire to be informed concerning the converted <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica:</hi> Take therefore a true Account of them in a few words.</p>
               <p>It is above forty Years since that truly godly Man, Mr. <hi>John Elliot,</hi> Pastor of the Church at <hi>Roxborough,</hi> (about a mile from <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi>) being warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a holy Zeal of Converting the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericans,</hi> set himself to learn the <hi>Indian</hi> Tongue, that he might more easily and successfully <hi>(b)</hi> open to them the Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Gospel; upon account of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49297:52"/> which he has been (and not undeserved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) called, <hi>The Apostle of the American In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians.</hi> This Reverend Person, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out very great labour, translated the whole Bible into the <hi>Indian</hi> Tongue; <hi>(c)</hi> he translated also several <hi>English</hi> Treatises of Practical Divinity and Catechisms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Language. Above 26 Years ago he gathered a Church of Converted <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in a Town called <hi>(d) Natick;</hi> these <hi>Indians</hi> confess'd their sins with Tears, and professed their Faith in Christ, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they and their Children were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and they were solemnly joyned together in a <hi>Church Covenant;</hi> the said Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> was the first that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred the Lord's Supper to them. The Pastor of that Church now is an <hi>Indian,</hi> his name is <hi>Daniel.</hi> Besides this Church at <hi>Natick,</hi> among our Inhabitants in the <hi>Massachusets.</hi> Colony, there are four <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Assemblies, <hi>(e)</hi> where the Name of the True God and Jesus Christ is solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called upon; these Assemblies have some <hi>American</hi> Preachers. Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly used to Preach to them once every fortnight, but now he is weakned with Labours and old Age, being in the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fourth Year of his Age, and Preacheth not to the <hi>Indians</hi> oftner than once in two Months.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:49297:53"/>
               <p>There is another Church, consisting only of Converted <hi>Indians,</hi> about fifty Miles from hence, in an <hi>Indian</hi> Town call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Mashippaug:</hi> The first Pastor of that Church was an <hi>English</hi> Man, who being skilful in the <hi>American</hi> Language, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Gospel to them in their own Tongue. <hi>(f)</hi> This <hi>English</hi> Pastor is dead, and instead of him that Church has an <hi>Indian</hi> Preacher.</p>
               <p>There are, besides that, five Assemblies of <hi>Indians</hi> professing the Name of <hi>Christ,</hi> not far distant from <hi>Mashippaug,</hi> which have <hi>Indian</hi> Preachers; <hi>(g) John Cotton,</hi> Pastor of the Church at <hi>Plymouth</hi> (Son of my venerable Father-in-law <hi>John Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> formerly the famous Teacher of the Church at <hi>Boston</hi>) hath made very great progress in learning the <hi>Indian</hi> Tongue, and is very skilful in it; he Preaches in their own Language to the last five men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Congregations every Week. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over of the Inhabitants of <hi>Saconet</hi> in <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> Colony, there is a great Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of those who for distinction sake are called <hi>Praying Indians,</hi> because they Pray to God in Christ.</p>
               <p>Not far from a Promontory called <hi>Cape-Cod,</hi> there are six Assemblies of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> who are to be reckoned as <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:49297:53"/> amongst whom there are six <hi>Indian</hi> Preachers, <hi>Samuel Treat,</hi> Pastor of a Church at <hi>Eastham,</hi> Preacheth to those Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in their own Language. There are likewise amongst the Islanders of <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucket</hi> a Church, with a Pastor who was lately a <hi>Heathen,</hi> and several <hi>Meetings</hi> of <hi>Catechumens,</hi> who are instructed by the Converted <hi>Indians.</hi> There is also another Island about seven Leagues long (called <hi>Martha's Vineyard</hi>) where are two <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Churches planted, which are more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous than the rest, over one of which there presides an ancient <hi>Indian</hi> as Pastor, called <hi>Hiacooms: John Hiacooms,</hi> Son of the said <hi>Indian</hi> Pastor, also Preacheth the Gospel to his Country-men. In another Church in that place, <hi>John Tockinosh</hi> a Converted <hi>Indian</hi> teaches. In these Churches <hi>ruling Elders</hi> of the <hi>Indians</hi> are joyned to the Pastors: The Pastors were chosen by the People, and when they had fasted and prayed, Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> laid their Hands on them, so that they were solemnly Ordained. All the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations <hi>(h)</hi> of the Converted <hi>Indians</hi> (both the <hi>Catechumens</hi> and those in Church Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) every Lord's Day meet together; the Pastor or Preacher always begins with Prayer, and <hi>without a Form, because from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49297:54"/> the Heart;</hi> when the Ruler of the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly has ended Prayer, the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of <hi>Indians</hi> Praise God with singing, some of them are excellent Singers: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Psalm,</hi> he that Preaches reads a place of Scripture (one or more Verses as he will) and expounds it, gathers Doctrines from it, proves them by <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Reasons,</hi> and infers uses from them after the manner of the <hi>English,</hi> of whom they have been taught; then another Prayer to God in the Name of Christ concludes the whole Service. Thus do they meet together twice every Lord's-day. They observe no Holy-days but the Lord's Day, except upon some extraordinary occasion; and then they solemnly set apart whole Days, either in giving Thanks, or Fasting and Praying with great fervor of Mind.</p>
               <p>Before the <hi>English</hi> came into these Coasts, these barbarous Nations were altogether ignorant of the true God; hence it is that in their Prayers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons they use <hi>English</hi> words and terms; he that calls upon the most holy Name of God, says <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Lord;</hi> and also they have learned and borrowed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Theological Phrases from us.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:49297:54"/>
               <p>In short, there are six Churches of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> and eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Assemblies of <hi>Catechumens,</hi> professing the Name of Christ: Of the <hi>Indians</hi> there are four and twenty who are Preachers of the Word of God; and besides these, there are four <hi>English</hi> Ministers who preach the Gospel in the <hi>Indian</hi> Tongue. <hi>(i)</hi> I am now my self weary with writing, and I fear lest if I should add more, I should also be tedious to you; yet one thing I must add (which I had almost forgot) that there are many of the <hi>Indians</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who have learned by Heart the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techism, either of that famous Divine <hi>William Perkins,</hi> or that put forth by the Assembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and in their own Mother Tongue can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to all the Questions in it.</p>
               <p>But I must end: I salute the <hi>famous Professors</hi> in your University, to whom I desire you to communicate this Letter, as written to them also.</p>
               <p>Farwel, <hi>worthy Sir;</hi> the Lord preserve your Health for the benefit of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, his Church, and of Learning.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours ever,</hi> Increase Mather.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>New-Engl.</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>July</hi> 12. 1687.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:49297:55"/>
               <div n="(a)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> The Success of the Gospel in the <hi>EAST-INDIES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter the writing of <hi>this</hi> Letter, there came one to my Hands from the famous Dr. <hi>Leusden,</hi> together with a new and fair Edition of his <hi>Hebrew Psalter,</hi> Dedicated unto the Name of my absent Parent. He therein informs me, That our Example had awakned the <hi>Dutch</hi> to make some noble Attempts for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the Gospel in the <hi>East-Indies;</hi> besides what memorable things were done by the Excellent <hi>Robert Junius,</hi> in <hi>formosa,</hi> fifty years ago. He also informs me, That in and near the Island of <hi>Ceylon,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Pastors have Baptized about three hundred thousand of <hi>Eastern Indians;</hi> for altho' the Ministers are utterly ignorant of their Language, yet here are <hi>School-Masters</hi> who teach them, The <hi>Lord's Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> the <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> a <hi>Morning Prayer,</hi> an <hi>Evening Prayer,</hi> a <hi>Blessing</hi> before Meat, and <hi>another after;</hi> and the Minister in his Visits being assured by the Master, who of them has learn'd all of them <hi>seven</hi> things, he thereupon counts they have such a perfect number of Attainments, that he presently <hi>Baptizes</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:49297:55"/> them. The pious Reader will doubtless bless God for <hi>this;</hi> but he will easily see that <hi>one</hi> of our Converted <hi>Indians</hi> has cost more pains than many of those; more <hi>thorough work</hi> has been made with them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(b)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s way of opening the Mysteries of the Gospel to our <hi>Indians.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>'TWas in the Year 1646, that Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> accompany'd by three more, gave a visit unto an Assembly of <hi>Indians,</hi> of whom he desired a Meeting at such a time and place, that he might lay before them the things of their Eternal Peace. After a serious <hi>Prayer,</hi> he gave them a <hi>Sermon,</hi> which continued about a quarter above an hour, and contained the principal Articles of the Christian Religion, applying all to the condition of the <hi>Indians</hi> present. Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, he asked them, whether they understood? and with a general reply they answered, <hi>They understood all.</hi> He then began what was his usual method after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in treating with them; that is, he caused them to propound such <hi>Questions</hi> as they pleas'd, unto himself; and he gave wise and good <hi>Answers</hi> to them all. Their <hi>Questions</hi> would often, tho not always, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to what he had newly Preached; and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49297:56"/> he this way not only made a <hi>Proof</hi> of their profiting by his Ministry, but also gave an <hi>Edge</hi> of what he delivered unto them. Some of their <hi>Questions</hi> would be a little <hi>Philosophical,</hi> and required a good measure of Learning in the Minister concerned with them; but for this our <hi>Eliot</hi> wanted not. He would also put proper <hi>Questions</hi> unto them, and at one of his first Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses with them, he made the young ones capable of regarding these three Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>Q. 1. <hi>Who made you and all the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. 2. <hi>Who do you look should save you from Sin and Hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. 3. <hi>How many Commandments has the Lord given you to keep?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was his Wisdom that he began with them upon such Principles, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves had already had some notion of; such as that of an <hi>Heaven</hi> for good, and <hi>Hell</hi> for bad People, when they <hi>Dy'd.</hi> It broke his gracious Heart within him to see, what Floods of Tears fell from the Eyes of several among these Degenerate Salvages, at the first Addresses which he made unto them; yea, from the very worst of them all. He was very inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to learn who were the <hi>Powaws,</hi> that is, the <hi>Sorcerers</hi> and <hi>Seducers,</hi> that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49297:56"/> the Worship of the Devil in any of their Societies; and having in one of his first Journies to them, found out one of those Wretches, he made the <hi>Indian</hi> come unto him, and said, <hi>Whether do you suppose</hi> God, <hi>or</hi> Chepian <hi>(i. e. the Devil) to be the Author of all good?</hi> The Conjurer answered, <hi>God.</hi> Upon this, he added with a stern Countenance, <hi>Why do you pray to</hi> Chepian <hi>then?</hi> and the poor Man was not able to stand or speak before him; but at last made promises of Reformation.</p>
                  <p>The Text which he first Preached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was that in Ezek. 37.9, 10. <hi>That by Prophesying to the Wind, the wind came, and the Dry Bones lived;</hi> and it was an obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation made by one, who then justly confessed, there was <hi>not much weight</hi> in it; that the word which the Indians use for <hi>wind,</hi> is <hi>wauban,</hi> and an Indian of that Name was one of the first that here zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously promoted the Conversion of his Neighbours. But having thus entred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Teaching</hi> of these poor Creatures, it's incredible how much time, toyl, and hardship, he underwent in the Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Undertaking; how many weary days and nights rolled over him; how many tiresome Journies he endur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and how many terrible dangers he
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49297:57"/> had experience of. If you briefly would know <hi>what</hi> he felt, and <hi>what</hi> carried him through all, take it in his own words, in a Letter to the Honourable Mr. <hi>Winslow,</hi> says he, <hi>I have not been dry night nor day, from the third day of the week unto the sixth, but so Travelled, and at night pull of my Boots, wring my Stockings, and on with them again, and so continue. But God steps in and helps. I have considered the word of God in</hi> 2 Tim. 2.3. Endure hardships as a good Souldier of Christ.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(c)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> His Translating the Bible, and other Books of Piety into the <hi>Indian Tongue.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ONe of his Remarkable Cares for these illiterate Indians, was to bring them into the use of <hi>Schools</hi> and <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ks.</hi> He quickly procured the benefit of <hi>Schools</hi> for them; wherein they profited so much, that not only very many of them came to <hi>Read</hi> and <hi>Write,</hi> but also several arrived unto a Liberal Education in our Colledge, and one or two of them took their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the rest of our <hi>Graduates.</hi> And for Books, 'twas his chief desire that the sacred Scriptures might not in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49297:57"/> Tongue be locked or hidden from them; very hateful and hellish did the policy of Popery appear to him on this account: Our <hi>Eliot</hi> was very unlike to that <hi>Franciscan,</hi> who writing into <hi>Europe,</hi> gloried much how many thousands of <hi>Indians</hi> he had converted; but added, <hi>That he desired his Friend would send him the Book called the</hi> Bible; <hi>for he had heard of there being such a Book in</hi> Europe, <hi>which might be of some use to him,</hi> No, our <hi>Eliot</hi> found he could not live without a Bible himself; he would have parted with all his Estate sooner than have lost a Leaf of it; and he knew it would be of more than some use unto the <hi>Indians</hi> too; he therefore with a vast labour translated the Holy Bible into the <hi>Indian</hi> Language. Behold, ye <hi>Americans,</hi> the greatest ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that ever you were partakers of! This Bible was printed here at our <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge;</hi> and it is the only Bible that ever was printed in all <hi>America,</hi> from the very foundation of the World. The whole Translation he writ with but one Pen; which Pen, had it not been lost, would have certainly deserved a richer Case than was bestow'd upon that Pen which <hi>Halland</hi> writ his Translation of <hi>Plutarch</hi> with. The Bible being justly made the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49297:58"/> Leader of all the rest, a little <hi>Indian</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary quickly followed; for besides Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and Grammars, and some other such Composures, we quickly had <hi>The Practice of Piety</hi> in the <hi>Indian</hi> Tongue; and the Reverend <hi>Richard Baxter's Call to the Unconverted;</hi> he also translated some of Mr. <hi>Shepherd's</hi> Composures; and such Catechisms likewise as there was occasion for. It cannot but be hoped that some Fish were to be made alive, since the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Sanctuary thus came unto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(d)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> His gathering of a Church at <hi>Natick.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Indians</hi> that had felt the Impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of his Ministry, were quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly distinguished by the name of Praying-<hi>Indians;</hi> and these <hi>Praying-Indians</hi> as quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were for a more decent, and <hi>English</hi> way of living, and they desired a more fixed Cohabitation. At several Places did they now combine and settle: But the Place of greatest name among their Towns. is that of <hi>Natick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here 'twas, that in the year 1651 those that had heretofore lived like the wild Beasts in the Wilderness, now compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themselves into a Town; and they first apply'd themselves to the forming of their Civil Government. Our General
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49297:58"/> Court, notwithstanding their exact study to keep these <hi>Indians</hi> very sensible of their being subject unto the <hi>English</hi> Empire, yet had allowed them their smaller Courts, wherein they might govern their own smaller Cases and Concers after their own particular modes, and might have their Town Orders, if I may call them so, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to themselves. With respect hereunto, Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> on a Solemn Fast made a publick Vow, <hi>That seeing these</hi> Indians <hi>were not prepossessed with any Forms of Government, he would instruct them into such a Form as we had written in the Word of God, that so they might be a People in all things ruled by the Lord.</hi> Accordingly, he expounded unto them the Eighteenth Chapter of <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus;</hi> and then they chose Rulers of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, of Fifties, of Tens; and therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all entred into this Covenant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">We are the Sons of <hi>Adam;</hi> We and our Forefathers have a long time been lost in our sins; but now the Mercy of the Lord beginneth to find us out again; therefore the Grace of Christ helping us, we do give our selves and our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto God, to be his People. He shall rule us in all our Affairs; The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, the Lord is our King; he will
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49297:59"/> save us; and the wisdom which God has taught us in his Book shall guide us. Oh Jehovah! Teach us wisdom; send thy Spirit into our hearts; take us to be thy People, and let us take thee to be our God.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such an opinion about the perfection of the Scripture had he, that he thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed himself upon this occasion; <hi>God will bring Nations into distress and perplexity, that so they may be forced unto the Scriptures; all Governments w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll be shaken, that men may be forced at length to pitch upon that firm foundation,</hi> The Word of God.</p>
                  <p>The little Towns of these <hi>Indians</hi> being pitched upon this Foundation, they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly obandoned that <hi>Polygamy</hi> which had heretofore been common among them; They made severe Laws against Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Drunkenness, and Sabbath-breaking, and other Immoralities; which they began to lament after the establishment of a Church-order among them, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the several Ordinances and Privileges of a Church Communion. The Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> have usually been very strict in their admissions to Church-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship, and required very signal demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations of a Repenting and a Believing Soul, before they thought men fit Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49297:59"/> to be entrusted with <hi>the Rights of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> But they seem'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to augment than abate their usual Strictness when the Examination of the <hi>Indians</hi> was to be performed. A day was therefore set apart, which they called <hi>Natootomeuhtenicusuk,</hi> or, a <hi>Day of asking Questions,</hi> when the Ministers of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Churches, assisted with all the best Interpreters that could be had, publickly examined a good number of these Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, about their Attainments both in Knowledge and in Vertue. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the great satisfaction then received, our Churches being willing to proceed surely, and therefore slowly, in raising them up to a Church state, which might be comprehended in our Consoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, the Indians were afterwards cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Considerable Assemblies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened for that purpose, to make open Confession of their Faith in God and Christ, and of the Efficacy which his word had upon them for their Conversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him; which Confessions being taken in writing from their mouths by able Interpreters, were scanned by the People of God, and found much accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with them.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:49297:60"/>
                  <p>I need pass no further censure upon them, than what is given by my Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, the well-known <hi>Richard Mather,</hi> in an Epistle of his, published on this occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; says he, <q rend="margQuotes">There is so much of God's Work among them, as that I cannot but count it a great Evil, yea, a great Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God and his Goodness, for any to make light of it. To see and hear <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> open their Mouths, and lifting up their Hands and Eyes in Prayer to the Living God, calling on him by his Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> in the Mediation of Jesus Christ, and this for a good while together; to see and hear them exhorting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Word of God; to see and hear them confessing the Name of Christ Jesus, and their own Sinfulness; sure this is more than usual! And tho they spoke in a Language, of which many of us understood but little, yet we that were present that day, we saw and heard them perform the Duties menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned with such grave and sober Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, with such comely reverence in their gesture, and their whole car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and with such plenty of Tears trickling down the Cheeks of some of them, as did argue to us that they spake with the holy Fear of God, and it much affected our hearts.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:49297:60"/>
                  <p>At length was a Church-state settled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: They entred as our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es do, into an holy Covenant, wherein they gave themselves, <hi>first unto the Lord, and then unto one another,</hi> to attend the Rules and Helps, and expect the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of the Everlasting Gospel; and Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> having a Mission from the Church of <hi>Roxbury</hi> unto the work of the Lord Christ among the <hi>Indians,</hi> conceived himself suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently authorized unto the performing of all Church-work about them; ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4. and he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly administred, first the Baptism, and then the Supper of the Lord unto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(e)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> The Hindrances and Obstructions that the Devil gave unto him.</head>
                  <p>WE find four Assemblies of Praying <hi>Indians</hi> besides that of <hi>Natick,</hi> in our Neighbourhood. But why no more? Truly, not because our <hi>Eliot</hi> was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Offers and Labours for their good; but because many of the obdurate Infidels would not receive the <hi>Gospel of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> In one of his Letters, I find him giving this ill report, with such a good reason for it; Lyn-<hi>Indians are all naught
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49297:61"/> save one, who sometimes comes to hear the word; and the reason why they are bad, is, principally because their</hi> Sachim <hi>is naught, and careth not to pray unto God.</hi> Indeed the <hi>Sachims,</hi> or the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Indians,</hi> generally did all they could that their Subjects might not entertain the Gospel; the <hi>Devils</hi> having the <hi>Sachims</hi> on their side, thereby kept their Possession of the People too. Their <hi>Pauwaws</hi> of Clergy-Men, did much to maintain the Interest of the Devils in this Wilderness, those <hi>Children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and Enemies of all Righteousness,</hi> did not cease <hi>to pervert the Right ways of the Lord;</hi> but their <hi>Sachims</hi> or Magistrates did more towards it; for they would presently raise a Storm of Persecution upon any of their Vassals that should Pray unto the Eternal God. The ground of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in them, was, an old Fear, that Religion would abridge them of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny which they had been us'd unto; they always, like the Devil, held their people in a most absolute servitude, and Rul'd by no Law, but by their Will, which left their poor Slaves nothing that they could call their own. They now suspected that Religion would put a Bridle upon such usurpations, and oblige them to a more Equal and Humane way of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49297:61"/> Government; they therefore, some of them, had the Impudence to address the <hi>English,</hi> that no motions about the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion might ever be made unto them; and Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> sometimes in the Wilderness, without the Company or Assistance of any other <hi>Englishman,</hi> has been treated in a very Threatning and Barbarous manner by some of these Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; but God inspir'd him with so much Resolution as to tell them, <hi>I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the work of the Great God, and my God is with me, so that I fear neither you, nor all the</hi> Sachims <hi>in the Country; I'll go on, and do you Touch me if you dare!</hi> Upon which the stoutest of them have shrunk and fell before him. And one of them, he at length Conquered by Preaching unto him a Sermon upon the <hi>Temptations</hi> of our Lord; particularly, the <hi>Temptations</hi> fetch'd from the Kingdoms and Glories of the World.</p>
                  <p>The little Kingdoms and Glories of the Great Men among the <hi>Indians,</hi> was a Powerful Obstacle to the success of Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Ministry; and it is observable, that several of those Nations which thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused the Gospel, quickly afterwards were so <hi>Devil-driven</hi> as to begin an unjust and bloody War upon the <hi>English,</hi> which issued
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49297:62"/> in their speedy and utter Extirpation from the Face of Gods Earth. It was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Remark'd, in <hi>Philip,</hi> the Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader of the most calamitous War that ever they made upon us; our <hi>Eliot</hi> made a Tender of the Everlasting Salvation to that King, but that <hi>Philip</hi> entertained it with contempt and anger, and after the <hi>Indians</hi> mode of joyning signs with words, he took a Button upon the Coat of the Reverend Man, adding, <hi>That he cared for his Gospel, just as much as he cared for that Button.</hi> The World has heard what a Terrible Ruine soon came upon that woful Creature, and upon all his people. It was not long before the hand which now Writes, upon a certain occasion took off the Jaw from the Blasphemous expos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Skull of that <hi>Leviathan;</hi> and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Samuel Lee</hi> is now Pastor to an <hi>English</hi> Congregation, sounding and show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Praises of Heaven, upon that very spot of ground, where <hi>Philip</hi> and his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> were lately Worshipping of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes the more immediate Hand of God, by cutting off the principal Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers of the Gospel among the <hi>Indians,</hi> made way for Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Ministry. As I remember, he relates, that an Association
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49297:62"/> of prophane <hi>Indians</hi> near our <hi>Weymouth,</hi> set themselves to deter and seduce the Neighbour <hi>Indians</hi> from the <hi>Right ways of the Lord.</hi> But God quickly sent the <hi>Small-Pox</hi> among them, which like a great Plague soon swept them away, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by engaged the rest unto himself. I need only to add, That one Attempt made by the Devil, to prejudice the <hi>Pagans</hi> against the Gospel, had something in it extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary. While Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> was Preaching of Christ unto the other <hi>Indians,</hi> a <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> appeared unto a Prince of the <hi>Eastern-Indians,</hi> in a shape that had some Resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> or of an <hi>English</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, pretending to be, <hi>The English-man's God.</hi> The Spectre commanded him, <hi>To forbear the drinking of Rum,</hi> and <hi>to observe the Sabbath-day,</hi> and <hi>to deal justly with his Neighbours;</hi> all which things had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated in Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Ministry; promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing therewithal unto him, That if he did so, at his Death his Soul should ascend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a happy Place; otherwise descend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Miseries; but the Apparition all the while, never said one word about Christ, which was the main subject of Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Ministry. The <hi>Sachim</hi> received such an Impression from the Apparition, that he dealt justly with all Men, except in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49297:63"/> bloody Tragedies and Cruelties he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards committed on the <hi>English</hi> in our Wars; he kept the Sabbath-day like a Fast, frequently attending in our Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; he would not meddle with any <hi>Rum,</hi> tho usually his Country-men had rather dye than undergo such a piece of Self-denial; that Liquor has meerly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted them. At last, and not long since, this <hi>Daemon</hi> appear'd again unto this <hi>Pagan,</hi> requiring him to kill himself, and assuring him that he should revive in a day or two, never to dye any more. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon divers times attempted it, but his Friends very carefully prevented it; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever at length he found a fair Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for this fowl Business, and hanged himself; you may be sure, without his expected <hi>Resurrection.</hi> But it is easie to see what a stumbling-block was here laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the miserable <hi>Indians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="(f)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> The <hi>Indian</hi>-Churches at <hi>Maship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paug,</hi> and elsewhere.</head>
                  <p>THE same Spirit which acted Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> quickly inspired others else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, to prosecute the work of rescuing the poor <hi>Indians</hi> out of their worse than <hi>Egyptian</hi>-Darkness, in which Evil Angels
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49297:63"/> had been so long preying upon them. One of these was the godly and gracious <hi>Richard Bourn,</hi> who soon saw a great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his holy Labours. In the Year 1666. Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> accompanied by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Governour, and several Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates and Ministers of <hi>Plymouth</hi>-Colony procured a vast Assembly at <hi>Mashippaug;</hi> and there a good number of <hi>Indians</hi> made Confessions touching the <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Belief,</hi> and <hi>Regeneration</hi> of their Souls, with such Understanding and Affection, as was extreamly grateful to the Pious Auditory. Yet such was the strictness of the good People in this Affair, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would countenance the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of <hi>these Indians</hi> unto <hi>Church-Fellowship,</hi> they ordered their Confessions to be written and sent unto all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Colony for their Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but so approved they were, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Messengers of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches giving their presence and consent, they became a Church, and chose Mr. <hi>Bourn</hi> to be their Pastor; who was then by Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> Ordain'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Office over them. From hence Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> went over to an Island called <hi>Martha</hi>'s <hi>Vineyard,</hi> where <hi>God</hi> had so succeeded the honest Labours of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49297:64"/> some, and particularly of the <hi>Mayhew</hi>'s, as that a Church was gathered.</p>
                  <p>This Church, after <hi>Fasting and Prayer,</hi> chose one <hi>Hiacooms</hi> to be their Pastor, <hi>John Tockinosh,</hi> an able and discreet <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> to be their Teacher; <hi>Joshua Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meecheegs</hi> and <hi>John Nanaso</hi> to be ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and these were then Ordain'd by Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> thereunto. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Habitation caused this one Church by mutual Agreemant afterwards to become two; the Pastor and one ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elder taking one part, and the Teacher and one ruling Elder another; and at <hi>Nantucket,</hi> another adjacent Island, was another Church of <hi>Indians</hi> quickly gathered, who chose an <hi>Indian, John Gibs,</hi> to be their Minister. These Churches are so exact in their Admission, and so solemn in their Discipline, and so serious in their Communion, that some of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian English</hi> in the Neighbourhood, which would have been loth to have mixed with them in a <hi>Civil Relation,</hi> yet have gladly done it a <hi>Sacred One.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis needless for me to repeat what my Father has written about the other <hi>Indian</hi> Congregations; only there having been made mention of one <hi>Hiacooms,</hi> I am will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to annex a Passage or two concerning
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49297:64"/> that memorable <hi>Indian.</hi> That <hi>Indian</hi> was a very great Instrument of bringing his <hi>Pagan</hi> and wretched Neighbours, to a saving acquaintance with our Lord Jesus Christ; and God gave him the honour, not only of so doing much for some, but also of <hi>suffering</hi> much from others, of those unhappy Salvages. Once particularly, this <hi>Hiacooms</hi> received a cruel blow from an <hi>Indian</hi> Prince, which, if some <hi>English</hi> had not been there, might have killed him, for his Praying unto God. And afterwards he gave this account of his Trial in it; said he, <hi>I have two hands; I had one hand for Injuries, and the other for God; while I did receive wrong with the one, the other laid the greater hold on God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, the <hi>Powaws</hi> did use to hector and abuse the Praying <hi>Indians</hi> at such a rate, as terrified others from joyning with them; but once when those <hi>Witches</hi> were bragging that they could kill all the <hi>Praying Indians</hi> if they would; <hi>Hiacooms</hi> repli'd, <hi>Let all the</hi> Powaws <hi>in the Island come together, I'll venture my self in the midst of them; let them use all their VVitchcrafts, with the help of God I'll tread upon them all.</hi> By this courage he silenced the <hi>Powaws;</hi> but at the same time also he heartned the People, at such a rate as was truly won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49297:65"/> nor could any of them ever harm this Eminent Confessor afterwards; nor indeed any <hi>Proselite</hi> which had been by his means brought home to God; yea, 'twas observed after this, that they rather kill'd than cur'd all such of the Heathen as would yet make use of their Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for help against their Sickness.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(g)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(g)</hi> Of Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Fellow-Labourers in the <hi>Indian-work.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SO little was the Soul of our <hi>Eliot</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with any Envy, as that he longed for nothing more than Fellow-Labourers, that might move and shine in the same Orb with himself; he made his cries both to God and Man, for more Labourers to be thrust forth into the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Harvest; and indeed it was an Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest of so few secular Advantages and Encouragements, that it must be nothing less than a Divine Thrust, which could make any to labour in it. He saw the answer of his Prayers, in the Generous and Vigorous Attempts made by several other most worthy Preachers of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to Gospelize our perishing Indians. At the writing of my Father's Letter there were four; but the Number of them
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49297:65"/> increases apace among us. At <hi>Martha</hi>'s <hi>Vineyard,</hi> the old Mr. <hi>Mayhew,</hi> and seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Sons, and Grand-sons, have done very worthily for the Souls of the Indians; there were fifteen years ago, by Computation, about fifteen hundred Seals of their Ministry upon that one Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. In <hi>Connecticut,</hi> the holy and acute Mr. <hi>Fitch,</hi> has made noble Essays, towards the Conversion of the Indians; but, I think, the Prince he has to deal withal, being an obstinate Infidel, gives unhappy Remora's to the Successes of his Ministry. And godly Mr. <hi>Pierson</hi> has in that Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deserved well, if I mistake not, upon the same account. In <hi>Massachusets</hi> we see at this day, the pious Mr. <hi>Daniel Gookin,</hi> the gracious Mr. <hi>Peter Thatcher,</hi> the well-accomplished and industrious Mr. <hi>Grindal Rawson,</hi> all of them hard at work, to turn these poor Creatures <hi>from Darkness unto Light, and from Satan unto God.</hi> In <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> we have the most active Mr. <hi>Samuel Treat,</hi> laying out himself to save this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; and there is one Mr. <hi>Tupper,</hi> who uses his laudable Endeavours for the Instruction of them.</p>
                  <p>'Tis my Relation to him, that causes me to defer unto the last place, the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of Mr. <hi>John Cotton,</hi> who addresses
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49297:66"/> the <hi>Indians</hi> in their own Language with an admirable Dexterity, and has done more than a little Service for them. He hired an <hi>Indian,</hi> after the rate of twelve Pence <hi>per</hi> Day for fifty Days, to teach him the <hi>Indian Tongue;</hi> but his knavish Tutor having received his whole pay too soon, ran away before twenty Days were out; however, in this time he had profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted so far, that he could Preach unto the Natives; and he has ever since been do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much for God among them. Having told my Reader, that the Second Edition of the <hi>Indian</hi> Bible was wholly of his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Amendment; because it is not proper for me to say much of him, I shall only add this remarkable Story: Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> accompany'd by the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Major General, and sundry Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Quality, made a Journey to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Indians</hi> in the Neighbourhood, with a free <hi>offer of the Words whereby they might be Saved.</hi> The Prince took time to consider of it, and according to the true <hi>English</hi> of taking time in such cases, at length he told them, <hi>He did not accept the Tender which they made him.</hi> They then took their leaves of him, not without first giving him this plain and short Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, <hi>If God have any Mercy for your
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49297:66"/> miserable People, he will quickly find away to take you out of the way.</hi> 'Twas presently after this, that this Prince going forth to a Battel against another Nation of <hi>Indians,</hi> was killed in the Fight; and the young <hi>Prince</hi> being in his Minority, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fell into the hands of Protectors, which favoured the Interest of the Gospel. Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> being advised of it, speedily and prosperously renewed the Tidings of an Eternal Saviour to the Salvages, who have ever since attended upon his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry; and the young <hi>Sachim,</hi> after he came to Age, expressed his Approbation of the Christian Religion; especially, when a while since he lay a Dying of a tedious Distemper, and would keep read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Mr. <hi>Baxter's Call to the Unconverted,</hi> with floods of Tears in his Eyes, while he had any strength to do it.</p>
                  <p>Such as these are the Persons whom our <hi>Eliot</hi> left engag'd in the <hi>Indian</hi> work, when, he departed from his Employment, unto his Recompence. And these Gentlemen are so indefatigable in their Labours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Indians,</hi> as that the most equal Judges must acknowledge them worthy of much greater Salaries than they are generously contented with. But one may see then who inspired that clamorous
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49297:67"/> (tho contemptible and blasted) Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of this Country, who very zealously Addressed the late A. B. of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that these Ministers might be deprived of their little Stipends, and that the said Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends might go to maintain that way of Worship among us, which the Plantation was erected on purpose for the peaceable avoiding of.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(h)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(h)</hi> The sacred and solemn Exercises perform'd in the <hi>Indian</hi> Congregations.</head>
                  <p>MY Father's account of the Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses performed in the <hi>Indian</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, will tell us what a blessed Fruit our <hi>Eliot</hi> saw of his Labours, before he went unto those Rewards which God had reserv'd in the Heavens for him. Some of the <hi>Indians</hi> quickly built for themselves good and large Meeting-houses, after the <hi>English</hi> Mode, in which also after the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> Mode they attended the <hi>things of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> And some of the <hi>English</hi> were helpful to them upon this account; among whom I ought particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to mention that Learned, Pious and Charitable Gentleman, the Worshipful <hi>Samuel Sewal</hi> Esq; who at his own Charge built a Meeting-house for one of the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:49297:67"/> Congregations, and gave those <hi>Indians</hi> cause to pray for him under that Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, <hi>He loveth our Nation, for he hath built us a Synagogue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It only remains that I give a touch or two upon the Worship which is attended in the Synagogue of the <hi>Indians.</hi> And first, the very Name of <hi>Praying Indians</hi> will assure us, that Prayer is one of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions; be sure they could not be our <hi>Eliot</hi>'s Disciples if it were not so. But how do they pray? we are told it is <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Form, because from the Heart;</hi> which is, as I remember, <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Expression concerning the Prayers in the Assemblies of the Primitive Christians; namely, <hi>sine monitore quia de pectore.</hi> It is evident, that the Primitive Christians had no stated <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies</hi> among them; that no <hi>Forms of Prayers</hi> were in their times imposed upon the Ministers of the Gospel; that even about the platform of <hi>Prayer</hi> given us by our Lord, it was the Opinion of <hi>Augustin</hi> himself, notwithstanding the advances made in his Age towards what we count <hi>Superstitious, that our Lord therein taught not what words we should use in Prayer, but what things we should pray for.</hi> And whatever scoffs the profanity of our days has abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that <hi>Phrase</hi> and <hi>thing</hi> withal, <hi>Gregory
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49297:68"/> Nazianzen</hi> in his days counted it the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Father's publick Prayers, <hi>that he had them from, and made them by the Holy Spirit.</hi> Our <hi>Indians</hi> accordingly find, that if they study the words of God, and their own Sins, and Wants, and Woes, they shall soon come to that attainment, <hi>Behold they pray!</hi> They can pray with much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence and enlargement; and would much wonder at it, if they should hear of an <hi>English Clergy</hi> that should <hi>read their Prayers out of a Book,</hi> when they should <hi>pour out their Souls</hi> before the God of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Their <hi>Preaching</hi> has much of <hi>Eliot,</hi> and therefore you may be sure much of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> but perhaps more of the Christian than of the Scholar in it. I know not how to describe it better, than by reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Heads of a Sermon, uttered by an <hi>Indian,</hi> on a <hi>Day of Humiliation</hi> kept by them, at a time when great Rains had given much damage to their Fruits and Fields; 'Twas on this wise: <hi>A little I shall say, according to that little I know.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="sermon">
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>Gen. 8.20, 21.</bibl>
                                 <hi>And</hi> Noah <hi>built an Altar to Jehovah; he took of every clean Beast, and of every
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49297:68"/> clean Fowl, and offered burnt-offerings on the Altar. And the Lord smelled a sweet Savour, and the Lord said in his Heart, I will not again Curse the Ground.</hi>
                              </q>
                              <q rend="margQuotes">
                                 <p>In that <hi>Noah</hi> sacrificed, he shew'd himself thankful; in that <hi>Noah</hi> worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he shewed himself godly. In that he offered clean Beasts, he shewed that God is an holy God. And all that come to God must be pure and clean. Know, that we must by Repentance purge our selves; which is the Work we are to do this Day.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Noah</hi> sacrificed, and so worshipped. This was the manner of old time. But what Sacrifices have we now to offer? I shall answer by that in <hi>Psal.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Offer to God the Sacrifice of Righteousness, and put your trust in the Lord</hi> These are the true Spiritual Sacrifices which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth at our hands; the <hi>Sacrifices of Righteousness;</hi> that is, we must look to our Hearts and Ways, that they be <hi>Righteous;</hi> and then we shall be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God when we worship him. But if we be unrighteous, unholy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, we shall not be accepted, our Sacrifices will be stark naught. Again, we are <hi>to put our trust in the Lord.</hi> Who else is there for us to trust in? We must
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49297:69"/> believe in the Word of God, if we doubt of God, or doubt of his Word, our Sacrifices are little worth; but if we trust stedfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in God, our Sacrifices will be good.</p>
                                 <p>Once more, what Sacrifices must we offer? My answer is, we must offer such as <hi>Abraham</hi> offered. And what a Sacrifice was that? We are told in <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Now I know that thou fearest me, seeing thou hast not withheld thy Son, thy only Son from me.</hi> It seems he had but one dearly beloved Son, and he offered that Son to God; and so God said, <hi>I know thou fearest me!</hi> Behold, a Sacrifice indeed and in truth! such an one must we offer. Only, God requires not us to Sacrifice our Sons, but our Sins; our dearest Sins. God calls us this day to part with all our Sins, tho' never so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved; and we must not withhold any of them from him. If we will not part with all, the Sacrifice is not right. Let us part with such Sins as we love best, and it will be a good Sacrifice.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>God smelt a sweet savour in</hi> Noah's <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice;</hi> and so will God receive our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, when we worship him aright. But how did God manifest his accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Offering? 'Twas by promising to drown the World no more,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49297:69"/> but give us fruitful Seasons. God has chastised us of late, as if he would ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly drown us; and he has drowned, and spoiled, and ruined a great deal of our Hay, and threatens to kill our Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel. 'Tis for this that we Fast and Pray this Day. Let us then offer a clean and pure Sacrifice, as <hi>Noah</hi> did; so God will smell a savour of Rest, and he will withhold the Rain, and bless us with such Fruitful Seasons as we are desiring of him.</p>
                              </q>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thus Preached an Indian called <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shokkon,</hi> above thirty years ago; and since that, I suppose, they have grown a little further into the <hi>New-English</hi> way of Preaching: You may have in their Sermons a <hi>Kukkeoromwohteaonk,</hi> that is, a Doctrine, <hi>Nahtootomwehteaonk,</hi> or, an Answer, a <hi>Witcheayeuonk,</hi> or, a Reason with an <hi>Ouwoteank,</hi> or, an Use for the close of all.</p>
                  <p>As for Holy-days, you may take it for granted, our <hi>Eliot</hi> would not perswade his Indians to any stated ones. Even the <hi>Christmas-Festival</hi> it self, he knew to be a stranger unto the Apostolical times; that the exquisite <hi>Vossius</hi> himself acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, 'twas not celebrated in the First or Second Century: And that there is a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49297:70"/> Truth in the words of the great <hi>Chemuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Anniversarium Diem Natalis Christi, celebratum fuisse, apud vetussimos nunquam leginur.</hi> It was his Opinion, that if the <hi>Day of our Lord's Nativity</hi> were to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, it should not be in <hi>December:</hi> that many Churches for divers Ages kept it not in <hi>December,</hi> but in <hi>January;</hi> that <hi>Chrysostom</hi> himself, about four hundred Years after our Saviour, excuses the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of the <hi>December</hi>-season for it, and confesses it had not been kept above ten years at <hi>Constantinople:</hi> No, that it should be rather in <hi>September,</hi> in which Month the <hi>Jews</hi> kept the Feast that was a Type of our Lord's Incarnation; and <hi>Solomon</hi> also brought the <hi>Ark</hi> into the Temple, for our Lord was thirty years old when he entred upon his publick Ministry; and he continued in it three years and an half; now his Death was in <hi>March,</hi> and it is easie then to calculate when his Birth ought to be. He knew that indeed God had hid this Day, as he did the Body of <hi>Moses,</hi> to prevent Idolatry; but that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist</hi> had chose this Day to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the <hi>Pagans</hi> in their licencious and their debauched <hi>Saturnalia;</hi> and that a <hi>Tertullian</hi> would not stick to say, <hi>Shall we Christians, who have nothing to do with the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49297:70"/> Festivals of the</hi> Jews, <hi>which were of Divine Institution, embrace the</hi> Saturnalia <hi>of the Heathen? How do the</hi> Gentiles <hi>shame us, who are more true to their Religion than we are to ours? None of them will observe the Lord's Day, for fear lest they should be</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; <hi>and shall not we then by observing their Festivals, fear lest we be made</hi> Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks? In fine, it was his Opinion, That for us to have stated Holy-days, which are not appointed by the Lord Jesus Christ, is a deep Reflection upon the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of that Gracious Lord; and he brought up his <hi>Indians</hi> in the Principles which the old <hi>Waldenses</hi> had about such non-instituted Holy-days.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheless, he taught them to set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part their Days both for Fasting and Prayer, and for Feasting and Praise, when there should be <hi>extraordinary Occasions</hi> for them; and they perform the Duties of these Days with a very laborious Piety. One Party of the <hi>Indians</hi> long since, of their own accord, kept a <hi>Day of Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> together, wherein one of them dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed upon <hi>Psal.</hi> 66.7. <hi>He rules by his power for ever, his eyes behold the nations: let not the rebellious exalt themselves.</hi> And when one asked them afterwards, what was their reason of their keeping such a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49297:71"/> Day? they reply'd, <hi>It was to obtain five Mercies of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">First, That God would slay the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of their Hearts. Next, That they might love God and one another. Thirdly, That they might withstand the Temptations of Wicked Men, so that they might not be drawn back from God. Fourthly, That they might be Obedient unto the Counsels and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of their Rulers. Fifthly, That they might have their Sins done away by the Redemption of Jesus Christ. And lastly, That they might walk in the good ways of the Lord.</q> I must here embrace my opportunity to tell the World, That our cautious <hi>Eliot</hi> was far from the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of those who have thought it not only warrantable, but also commendable to Adopt some Heathenish Usages into the Worship of God, for the more easie and speedy gaining of the Heathen to that Worship. The policy of treating the <hi>Pagan</hi> Rites as the <hi>Jews</hi> were to do Captives, before they married them, to shave their Hair, and pare their Nails, our <hi>Eliot</hi> counted as ridiculous as pernicious. He knew that the Idolatries and Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Popery, were founded in this way of Proselyting the barbarous Nations,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49297:71"/> which made their Descent upon the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire; and he look'd upon the like methods which the Protestants have used, that they might ingratiate themselves with the Papists, and that our Separation from them should become less dangerous and sensible, to be the most sensible and dangerous wound of the Reformation. Wherefore, as no less a Man than D. <hi>Henry Moor</hi> says about our Compliances with the <hi>Papists,</hi> which are a sort of <hi>Pagans, Their Conversion and Salvation being not to be compassed by needless Symbolizing with them in any thing, I conceive our best policy is studiously to imitate them in nothing, but for all indifferent things, to think rather the worse of them for their using of them. As no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Honour would willingly go in the known Garb of infamous Persons. Whatsoever we court them in, they do but turn it to our scorn and contempt, and are the more hardned in their own wickedness.</hi> To act upon this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, is the design and glory of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land!</hi> And our <hi>Eliot</hi> was of this Perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he brought his <hi>Indians</hi> to a pure, plain, Scripture Worship. He would not gratifie them with a <hi>Samaritan</hi> sort of blended, mixed Worship; and he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, as well he might, that the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi>'s first Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49297:72"/> enough in it, for ever to deter us all from such unhapyy Temporizing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="(i)" type="note">
                  <head>
                     <hi>(i)</hi> A Comparison between what the <hi>New-Englanders</hi> have done for the Conversion of the <hi>Indians,</hi> and what has been done elsewhere by the <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is to be confessed, That the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> have a Clergy so very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and so little encumbred, and are Masters of such prodigious Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Revenues, as renders it very easie for them to exceed the <hi>Protestants</hi> in their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to Christianize the <hi>Pagan</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages. Nor would I reproach, but rather applaud their industry in this matter, wishing that we were all touched with an Emulation of it. Nevertheless, while I commend their Industry, they do by their Clamours against the Reformed Churches upon this account, oblige me to tax divers very scandalous things in the <hi>Missions</hi> which they make <hi>pro propaganda fide</hi> throughout the World; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal to compare what has been done by that little handful of Reformed Churches in this Country, which has in divers regards out-done the furthest Efforts of Popery.</p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:49297:72"/>
                  <p>The attainments, which with God's help we have carried up our <hi>Indians</hi> unto, are the chief honour and glory of our Labours with them. The Reader will smile perhaps, when I tell him, that by an odd accident there are lately fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands, the Manuscripts of a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit,</hi> whom the <hi>French</hi> employed as a <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionary</hi> among the Western <hi>Indians;</hi> in which Papers there are both a <hi>Catechism</hi> containing the Principles which those Heathens are to be instructed in; and <hi>Cases of Conscience,</hi> referring to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations. The <hi>Catechism,</hi> which is in the <hi>Iroquoise</hi> Language (a Language re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable for this, that there is not so much as a <hi>Labial</hi> in it) with a Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on annexed, has one Chapter about <hi>Heaven,</hi> and another about <hi>Hell,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are such Thick skul'd passages as these.</p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>How is the Soil made in Heaven?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis a very <hi>fair Soyl;</hi> they want neither for <hi>Meats</hi> nor <hi>Clothes;</hi> 'tis but <hi>wishing,</hi> and we have them.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>Are they employ'd in Heaven?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, they do nothing; the Fields yield <hi>Corn, Beans, Pumpkins,</hi> and the like without any Tillage.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>What sort of Trees are there?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>'<hi>A.</hi> Always green, full and flourishing.</p>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:49297:73"/>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q.</hi> Have they in Heaven the same Sun, the same Wind, the same Thunder that we have here?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, the Sun ever shines; 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fair weather.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>But how their Fruits?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> In this one quality they exceed ours; that they are never wasted; you have no sooner pluckt one, but you see another presently hanging in its room. And after this rate goes on the <hi>Catechism</hi> concerning Heaven. Concerning Hell it thus discourses:</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>VVhat sort of a Soil is that of Hell?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A very wretched Soil; 'tis a fiery Pit, in the Center of the Earth.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>Have they any light in Hell?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, 'tis always dark; there's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Smoke there; their Eyes are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in pain with it; they can see no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Devils.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>VVhat shap'd things are the Devils?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Very ill shap'd things; they go about with Vizards on; and they ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie Men.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>VVhat do they eat in Hell?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> They are always hungry; but the damned feed upon hot Ashes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents there.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>VVhat water have they to drink?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:49297:73"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Horrid Water; nothing but melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lead.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>'Q. <hi>Don't they die in Hell?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, yet they eat one another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day; but anon God restores and renews the Man that was eaten, as a cropt Plant, in a little time repullulates.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>It seems they have not thought this Divinity too gross for the Barbarians. But I shall make no reflections on it; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly add one or two <hi>Cases of Conscience</hi> from their Directory.</p>
                  <p>'Tis one of their weighty Cases, <q rend="margQuotes"> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Christian be bound to pay his Whore her Hire, or no?</q> To this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bruias</hi> answers, <hi>Tho' he be bound in Justice to do it, yet in asmuch as the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> [and you must suppose their Whores to be such!] <hi>use to keep no Faith in such matters, the Christians may chuse whether they will keep any too.</hi> But Father <hi>Pierron</hi> with a most profound Learning answers, <hi>He is not bound unto it all; inasmuch as no Man thinks himself bound to pay a Witch that has enchanted him; and this business is pretty much akin to that.</hi> Another of their diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Cases, is, <q rend="margQuotes">Whether an <hi>Indian</hi> steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Hatchet from a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> be bound to make Restitution?</q> And it is very conscientiously determined. <q rend="margQuotes">That
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49297:74"/> if the <hi>Dutchman</hi> be one that has used a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Trade with other <hi>Indians,</hi> the Thief is not bound unto any Restitution; for 'tis certain, he gains more by such a Trade than the value of many Hatchets in a Year.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I'll tire my Reader with no more of this wretched stuff. But let him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that the Proselyted <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>New-England</hi> have been instructed at a more noble rate; we have helped them to the sincere Milk of the Word: We have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them the <hi>whole Bible</hi> in their own Language, we have laid before them such a <hi>Creed</hi> as the Primitive Believers had, with such Explications as we embark our own Souls upon the Assurance of. And God has blessed our Education of these poor Creatures in such a measure, that they can Pray and Preach to better Education (give me leave to say it) than multitudes of the <hi>Romish-Clergymen.</hi> We could have Baptized many Troops of <hi>Indians,</hi> if we would have used no other measures with them, than the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theirs at <hi>Maryland,</hi> where they Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized a great Crew of <hi>Indians,</hi> in some new Shirts, bestow'd upon them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them thereunto; but the <hi>Indians</hi> in a week or two, not knowing how to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49297:74"/> wash their shirts, when they were grown foul, came and made a motion, that the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> would give more shirts to them, or else they would Renounce their Baptism. No, 'tis a <hi>Thorough paced Christianity,</hi> without which we have not imagined our <hi>Indians</hi> Christianized.</p>
                  <p>Nor have we been acted with a <hi>Roman-Catholick Avarice</hi> and <hi>Falsity</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> in prosecuting of our Conversions; 'tis the Spirit of an ELIOT, that has all along directed us. 'Tis a Specimen of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish <hi>Avarice,</hi> that their Missionaries are very rarely employed but where Bever, and Silver, and vast Riches are to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by gained; their Ministry is but a sort of Engine, to enrich <hi>Europeans</hi> with the Treasures of the <hi>Indies;</hi> thus one escaped from Captivity among the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> told me, that the <hi>Spanish</hi> Friars had carried their Gospel into the spacious Country of <hi>California;</hi> but finding the <hi>Indians</hi> there to be extremely poor, they quickly gave other the work, because forsooth <hi>such a poor Nation was not worth Converting.</hi> Whereas the <hi>New-Englanders</hi> could expect nothing from their <hi>Indians.</hi> We are to feed them and cloath them rather than receive any thing from them, when we bring them home to God. Again, the Popish Falsity
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49297:75"/> disposes them to so much <hi>Legerdemain</hi> in their Applications, as is very disagreeable to the Spirit and Progress of the Gospel. My worthy Friend, <hi>Mynheer Daille,</hi> who has been sedulous and successful in his Ministry among the <hi>Maqua</hi>'s, assures me, that a <hi>French</hi> Predicator, having been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to bring over those <hi>Indians</hi> unto the Interest (not of our Saviour, so much as) of <hi>Canada,</hi> at last, for a cure of their Infidelity, told them, he would give them a sign of God's Displeasure at them for it; <hi>The Sun should such a day be put out.</hi> This terrify'd them at a sad rate, and with great admiration and expectation, they told the <hi>Dutch</hi> of what was to come to pass; the <hi>Dutch</hi> reply'd, <hi>This was no more than every Child among them could foretel; they all knew there would then be an Eclipse of the Sun, but (said they) speak to</hi> Monsieur, <hi>that he would get the Sun extinguish'd a day before, or a day after what he spoke of, and if he can do that, believe him.</hi> When the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> thus understood what a Trick the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> would have put upon them, they became irreconcileably prejudiced against all his offers; nor have the <hi>French</hi> been since able to gain much upon that considerable People. The <hi>New-England<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> have used no such Stratagems and Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries;
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49297:75"/>
'tis the pure light of truth, which is all that has been used for the effecting of the rude People, whom 'twas easie to have cheated into our Profession. Much less have we used that Popish Cruelty, which the Natives of <hi>America</hi> have by some other People been treated with. Even a Bishop of their own, hath publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very Tragical Histories of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Cruelties upon the <hi>Indians</hi> of this Western World. Such were those Cruelties, that the <hi>Indians</hi> at length declared, <hi>They had rather go to Hell with their Ancestors, than to the same Heaven which the</hi> Spaniards <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto.</hi> 'Tis indeed impossible to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon up, the various and exquisite Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities with which these execrable <hi>Spaniards</hi> murthered in less than fifty Years, no less than fifty Millions of the <hi>Indians;</hi> it seems this was their way of bringing them into the Sheepfold of our Merciful Jesus; but on the other side, the good People of <hi>New England</hi> have carried it with so much tenderness towards the Tawny Creatures among whom we live, that they would not own so much as one foot of Land in the Country, without a fair Purchase and Consent from the Natives that laid claim unto it; albeit we had a Royal Charter from the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49297:76"/> us in our Settlement upon this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. I suppose, 'twas in revenge upon us for this Conscientiousness, that the late oppressors of <hi>New-England,</hi> acknowledged no Man to have any Title at all, unto one <hi>Foot of Land</hi> in all our Colony. But we did, and we do think, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Banters of such Ill Men, that the <hi>Indians</hi> had not by their Paganism so for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all Right unto any of their Possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that the first pretended Christians that could, might violently and yet ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly seize upon them. Instead of this, the People of <hi>New England,</hi> knowing that some of the English were sufficiently covetous and encroaching, and that the <hi>Indians</hi> in streights are easily prevailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to sell their Lands, made a Law, <hi>That none should Purchase, or so much as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any Land of the</hi> Indians, <hi>without the allowance of the General Court.</hi> Yea, and some Lands which were peculiarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the <hi>Indians,</hi> our People, who were more careful of them than they were of themselves, made a Law, <hi>That they should never be bought out of their Hands.</hi> I suppose after this, it would surprise Mankind, if they should hear such won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Creatures as our late Secretary, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, <hi>This barbarous People were never
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49297:76"/> civilly treated by the late Government, who made it their business to encroach upon their Lands, and by degrees to drive them out of all.</hi> But, how many other Laws we made in favour of the <hi>Indians,</hi> 'tis not easie to reckon up. 'Twas one of our Laws, <q rend="margQuotes">That for the further Encouragement of the hopeful Work among them, for the Civilizing &amp; Christianizing of them, any <hi>Indian</hi> that should be brought unto Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and come to live orderly in any <hi>English</hi> Plantation, should have such Alotments among the <hi>English,</hi> as the <hi>English</hi> had themselves. And, that if a competent number of them, should so come on to Civility, as to be capable of a Township, the General Court should grant them Lands for a Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as they do unto the <hi>English;</hi>
                     </q> Altho we had already bought up their Claims unto our Lands. We likewise had our Laws. <hi>That if any of our Cattle did any damage to their Corn, we should make them ample Satisfaction; and that we should give them all manner of Assistance in Fencing of their Fields.</hi> And because the <hi>Indians</hi> are excessively given unto the Vice of <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenness,</hi> which was a Vice unknown to them, until the <hi>English</hi> brought Strong-drink in their way, we have had a severe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49297:77"/> Law against all selling or giving any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicating Liquors</hi> to them. It were well if this Law were more severely Executed.</p>
                  <p>By this time I hope I have stopp'd the Calumnious Exclamations of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> against the Churches of the Reformation, for neglecting to Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the Natives of the <hi>Indies.</hi> But let me take this occasion to address the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Indians</hi> of my own Country, into some of whose hands 'tis likely this little Book may come.</p>
                  <p>¶ <q rend="margQuotes">Behold ye <hi>Indians,</hi> what love, what care, what cost, has been used by the <hi>English</hi> here, for the Salvation of your Precious and Immortal Souls. It is not because we have expected any <hi>Temporal Advantage</hi> from you, that we have been thus concerned for your good: No, 'tis God that has caused us to desire his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in your Salvation; and our hearts have bled with pity over you, when we have seen how horribly the Devil Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed you in this, and destroyed you in another World. It is <hi>much</hi> that has been done for you, we have put you into a way to be happy both on <hi>Earth</hi> while you live, and in <hi>Heaven</hi> when ye Dye. What can you think will become of you, if you slight all these Glorious
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49297:77"/> offers! me thinks you should say to your selves, <hi>Vitoh woh kiisinne peh quoh humunan mishanantamog ne mohsag wadchanituonk!</hi> You all believe that your Teacher <hi>Eliot</hi> was a Good and a Brave Man, and you would count it your Blessedness to be for ever with him. Nevertheless, I am to tell you, that if you don't become Real, and Thorough, and Holy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, you shall never have a comfortable sight of him any more. You know how he has fed you, and cloath'd you, as well as Taught you; you know how his Bowels yerned over you, even as tho' you had been his Children, when he saw any Afflictions come upon you; but if he find you among the wicked, in the day of Judgment, which he so often warn'd you of, he will then be a Dreadful Witness against you; and when the Lord Jesus passes that se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tence on you, <hi>Depart ye Cursed into Everlasting Fire with the Devil and his Angels,</hi> even your own <hi>Eliot</hi> will then say, <hi>Amen,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it all. Now to deal plainly with you, there are two Vices, which many of you are too prone unto, and which are utterly inconsistent with a True Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity. One of those Vices is that of Idleness; if you had a Disposition to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49297:78"/> follow an honest Calling, what should hinder you from growing as Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in your Estates, as many of your English Neighbours? Whereas, you are now poor, mean, ragged, starved, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and miserable; and instead of being able, as your English Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours do, to support the Ordinances of God, you are beholden to them, not only for maintaining of those Blessed Ordinances among you, but for many other kindnesses. And have you indeed forgot the <hi>Commandment</hi> of God which has been so often laid before you, <hi>Six days shalt thou Labour!</hi> For shame apply your selves to such Labour as may bring you into more Handsome Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But the other of those Vices, is that of <hi>Drunkenness.</hi> There are godly <hi>English Neighbours,</hi> of whom you should learn to pray; but there are some of you that learn to Drink, of other profane, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched <hi>English Neighbours.</hi> Poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, 'tis by this Iniquity that Satan still keeps possession of many Souls among you, as much as if you were still in all your woful <hi>Heathenism;</hi> and how often have you been told, <hi>Drunkards shall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of God?</hi> I beseech you to be sensible of the mischiefs to which this
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49297:78"/> thing exposes you, and never dream of escaping the <hi>Vengeance of Eternal Fire,</hi> if you indulge your selves in this <hi>Accursed Thing.</hi> I have done, when I have wish'd that the <hi>Gospel</hi> of the Lord Jesus may always <hi>Run and be Glorified among you.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The <hi>Conclusion,</hi> or, <hi>Eliot</hi> Expiring,</head>
            <p>BY this time, I have doubtless made my Readers loth to have me tell what now remains of this little History; doubtless they are wishing that this <hi>John</hi> might have <hi>Tarried untill the Second coming of our Lord.</hi> But, alas, All devouring <hi>Death</hi> at last snatch'd him from us, and slighted all those Lamentations of ours, <hi>My Father, My Father, the Chariots of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and the Horsemen thereof!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he was become a sort of <hi>Miles Emeritus;</hi> and began to draw near his End, he grew still more Heavenly, more Savo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, more Divine, and Scented more of the Spicy Country at which he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to put ashore. As the Historian ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves, of <hi>Tiberius;</hi> That when his Life and Strength were going from him, his
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:49297:79"/> Vice yet remained with him; on the contrary, the Grace of this Excellent Man rather increased than abated, when every thing else was dying with him. 'Tis too usual with Old Men, that when they are past work, they are least sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of their inabilities and incapacities, and can scarce endure to see another succeeding them in any part of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. But our <hi>Eliot</hi> was of a Temper quite contrary thereunto; for finding many Months before his Expiration, That he had not Strength enough to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dify his Congregation with publick <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Sermons,</hi> he importun'd his People with some impatience to call another Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister; professing himself, unable to die with comfort, until he could se a good Successor Ordain'd, Settled and Fixed among them. For this Cause, he also cry'd mightily unto the Lord Jesus, our Ascended Lord, that he would give such a gift unto <hi>Rox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury;</hi> and he sometimes call'd his whole Town together, to joyn with him in a Fast for such a Blessing. As the return of their Supplications, our Lord quickly bestow'd upon them, a Person young in Years, but old in Discretion, Gravity and Experience; and one whom the Church of <hi>Roxbury</hi> hopes to find, <hi>A Pastor after God's own Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:49297:79"/>
            <p>It was Mr. <hi>Nehemiah Walter,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the unanimous Vote and Choice of the Church there, become the <hi>Pastor</hi> of <hi>Roxbury,</hi> immediately found the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Eliot</hi> Embracing and Cherishing of him, with the tender Affections of a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The good Old Man like Old <hi>Aaron</hi> as it were disrobed himself, with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable Satisfaction, when he beheld his Garments put upon a Son so dear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. After this, he for a year or two before his Translation, could scarce be perswaded unto any publick Service, but humbly pleaded, what none but he would ever have said, <hi>It would be a wrong to the Souls of the people, for him to do any thing among them, when they were supplyed so much to their Advantage otherwise.</hi> If I mistake not, the Last that ever he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was on a publick Fast; when he fed his People with a very distinct, and use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exposition upon the Eighty Third Psalm; and he concluded with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, begging his Hearers to pardon the poorness, and meanness and brokenness, (as he called it) of his Meditations, but added he, <hi>My dear Brother here, will by and by mend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But altho' he thus dismissed himself, as one so near to the Age of Ninety, might
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49297:80"/> well have done from his publick Labours; yet he would not give over his endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, in a more private Sphere, to <hi>Do good unto all.</hi> He had always been an Enemy to Idleness; any one that should look into the little <hi>Diary</hi> that he kept in his <hi>Almanacks</hi> would see that there was with him, <hi>No day without a Line;</hi> he was troubled when he saw how much Time was devoured by the slavery to <hi>Tobacco,</hi> which too many debase themselves unto; and now he grew old, he was desirous that his Work should hold pace with his Life; the less Time he saw left, the less was he willing to have lost. He ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that he could now do nothing to any purpose in any Service for God; and sometimes he would say with an Air peculiar to himself, <hi>I wonder for what the Lord Jesus Christ lets me live; he knows that now I can do nothing for him!</hi> And yet he could not forbear Essaying to do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for his dearest Lord; wherefore, thought he, <hi>What shall I do?</hi> And he then conceived, that tho' the <hi>English</hi> could not be benefited by any Gifts which he now fancied himself to have only the Ruines of, yet who can tell but the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro's</hi> might! He had long lamented it with a bleeding and burning passion, that
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:49297:80"/> the <hi>English</hi> used their <hi>Negro</hi>'s but as for Horses for their Oxen, and that so little care was taken about their precious and immortal Souls, he look'd upon it as a Prodigy, that any wearing the Name of Christians, should so much have the Heart of Devils in them, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and hinder the Instructions of the poor <hi>Blackamoores,</hi> and confine the Souls of their miserable Slaves to a destroying ignorance, meerly for fear of thereby losing the benefit of their Vassalage; but now he made a motion to the <hi>English</hi> within two or three miles of him, that at such a time and place they would send their <hi>Negro</hi>'s once a week unto him: For he would then Catechise them, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten them to the utmost of his power in the things of their Everlasting Peace; however, he did not live to make much progress in this Undertaking.</p>
            <p>At length when he was able to do little without doors, he try'd then to do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within; and one thing was this. A young Boy in the Neighbourhood, had in his Infancy fallen into a fire, so as to burn himself into a perfect Blindness; but this Boy being now grown to some big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the good old Man took him home to his house, with some intentions to make
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49297:81"/> a <hi>Scholar</hi> of him. He first informed him of and from the <hi>Scripture,</hi> in which the Boy so profited, that in a little time he could even Repeat many whole <hi>Chapters</hi> Verbatim, and if any other in Reading missed a word, he would mind them of it; yea, and an ordinary piece of Latin was become easie to the Lad; but hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own <hi>Eyes</hi> closed by Death, he could no longer help the poor Child a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the want of his.</p>
            <p>Thus, as the Aged <hi>Polycarp</hi> could say, <hi>These Eighty Six years have I served my Lord Jesus Christ; and he has been such a good Master to me all this while, that I will not now forsake him.</hi> Such a <hi>Polycarp</hi> was our <hi>Eliot;</hi> he had been so many years engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the sweet service of his dear Jesus, that he could not now give it over: 'Twas his Ambition and his Priviledge, <hi>to bring forth Fruit in old Age;</hi> and what veneration the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> paid unto that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> of theirs, we were upon the like Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts willing to give unto this <hi>Man of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While he was thus making his <hi>Retreat</hi> out of this evil World, his Discourses from time to time ran upon, <hi>The Coming of the Lord Jesus Christ;</hi> it was the Theme which he still had Recourse unto, and we
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49297:81"/> were sure to have something of <hi>this,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other Subject he were upon. On <hi>this</hi> he talk'd, of <hi>this</hi> he pray'd, for <hi>this</hi> he long'd, and especially when any bad News ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd, his usual reflection thereupon would be, <hi>Behold some of the Clouds in which we must look for the coming of the Son of Man.</hi> At last, his Lord, for whom he had been long wishing, <hi>Lord come, I have been a great while ready for thy coming!</hi> at last, I say, his Lord <hi>came,</hi> and fetched him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into the <hi>Joy of his Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He fell into some Languishments, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a <hi>Fever,</hi> which in a few days brought him into the Pangs (may I say? or Joys) of Death; and while he lay in these, Mr. <hi>Walter</hi> coming to him, he said unto him, <hi>Brother, Thou art welcome to my very Soul. Pray, Retire to my Study for me, and give me leave to be gone;</hi> meaning that he should not, by Petitions to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for his Life, detain him here. It was in these Languishments, that speaking about the Work of the Gospel among the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he did after this heavenly manner express himself, <hi>There is a Cloud</hi> (said he) <hi>a dark Cloud upon the Work of the Gospel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the poor</hi> Indians. <hi>The Lord revive and prosper that Work and grant it may live when I am dead. It is a Work which I
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:49297:82"/> have been doing much and long about. But what was the word I spoke last? I recal that word,</hi> My Doings: <hi>Alas, they have been poor and small and lean Doings, and I'll be the Man that shall throw the first stone at them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It has been observed, that they who have spoke many considerable things in their Lives, usually speak few at their Deaths. But it was otherwise with our <hi>Eliot,</hi> who after much Speech of and for God in his Life-time, uttered some things little short of <hi>Oracles</hi> on his Death bed; which, 'tis a thousand Pities, they were not more exactly regarded and recorded. Those Authors that have taken the pains to Collect, <hi>Apophthegmata Morentium,</hi> have not therein been unserviceable to the Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but the <hi>Apophthegms</hi> of a Dying <hi>Eliot</hi> must have had in them a Grace and a Strain truly extraordinary; and indeed the <hi>vulgar Error</hi> of the signal Sweetness in the Song of a <hi>Dying Swan,</hi> was a very <hi>Truth</hi> in our expiring <hi>Eliot;</hi> his last Breath smelt strong of Heaven, and was Articled into none but very gracious Notes; one of the last whereof, was, <hi>welcome Joy!</hi> and at last it went away, calling upon the standers by, to <hi>Pray, pray, pray!</hi> which was the thing in which so vast a Portion of it had been before employ'd.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:49297:82"/>
            <p>This was the Peace, in the end of this <hi>Perfect and upright Man;</hi> thus was there another Star fetched away to be placed among the rest that the third Heaven is now enriched with. He had once, I think, a pleasant Fear, that the old Saints of his Acquaintance, especially those two dearest Neighbours of his, <hi>Cotton</hi> of <hi>Boston,</hi> and <hi>Mather</hi> of <hi>Dorchester,</hi> which were got safe to Heaven before him, would suspect him to be gone the wrong way because he staid so long behind them. But they are now together with a blessed Jesus, <hi>behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Glory,</hi> and celebrating the high Praises of Him that has <hi>call'd them into his marvellous light.</hi> Whether <hi>Heaven</hi> was any more <hi>Heaven</hi> to him, because of his finding there so many <hi>Saints</hi> with whom he once had his Delicious and Celestial Intimacies, yea, and so many <hi>Saints</hi> which had been the Seals of his own Ministry, in this lower world, I cannot say; but it would be <hi>Heaven</hi> enough unto him, to go unto that <hi>Jesus,</hi> whom he had lov'd, preach'd, serv'd, and in whom he had been long assured, there does <hi>All fulness dwell.</hi> In that Heaven I now leave him: But not without <hi>Grynaeus</hi>'s Pathetical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations <hi>[O beatum illum dieum!]</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes"> Blessed will be the Day, O blessed the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:49297:83"/> Day of our Arrival to the glorious As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of Spirits, which this great Saint is now rejoicing with!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Bereaved <hi>New-England,</hi> where are thy Tears, at this ill boding Funeral? We had a Tradition among us, <q rend="margQuotes">That the Country could never perish as long as <hi>Eliot</hi> was alive.</q> But into whose hands must this <hi>Hippo</hi> fall, now the <hi>Austin</hi> of it is taken away? Our <hi>Elisha</hi> is gone, and now who must <hi>next year invade the Land?</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> have a saying, <hi>Quando Lumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria paetiuntur Eclipsin, malim signum est mundo:</hi> But I am sure, 'tis a dismal <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clipse</hi> that has now befallen our <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> World. I confess, many of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients fell into the vanity of esteeming the Reliques of the <hi>Dead Saints,</hi> to be the <hi>Towers</hi> and <hi>Ramparts</hi> of the place that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd them; and the <hi>dead Bodies</hi> of two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles in the City, made the Poet cry out,
<q>A Facie Hostilis duo propugnacula praesunt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If the Dust of <hi>dead Saints</hi> could give us any protection, we are not without it; here is a Spot of <hi>American</hi> Soil that will afford a rich Crop of it, at the <hi>Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Just.</hi> Poor <hi>New England</hi> has been as <hi>Glastenbury</hi> of old was called, <hi>A
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49297:83"/> Burying Place of Saints,</hi> But we cannot see a more terrible Prognostick than Tombs filling apace with such Bones, as those of the Renowned <hi>Eliot</hi>'s: The whole Building of this Country trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at the fall of such a Pillar.</p>
            <p>For many Months before he dy'd, he would often cheerfully tells us, <q rend="margQuotes">That he was shortly going to Heaven, and that he would carry a deal of good News thither with him; <hi>he said,</hi> He would carry Tidings to the Old Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>New England,</hi> which were now in Glory, that Church work was yet car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on among us: That the number of our Churches was continually encreas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and that the Churches were still kept as big as they were, by the daily additions of those that shall be saved.</q> But the going of such as he from us, will apace diminish the occasions of such hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py tidings,</p>
            <p>What shall we now say? Our <hi>Eliot</hi> himself used most affectionately to bewail the Death of all useful Men; yet if one brought him the notice of such a thing, with any Dispondencies, or said, <hi>O Sir, such a one is Dead, what shall we do?</hi> He would answer, <hi>Well, but God lives, Christ lives, the Old Saviour of</hi> New England <hi>yet
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:49297:84"/> lives, and he will Reign till all his Enemies are made his Footstool.</hi> This and only this consideration have we to relieve us; and let it be accompanied with our addresses to the <hi>God of the Spirits of all Flesh,</hi> That there may be <hi>Timothies</hi> raised up in the room of our departed <hi>Pauls;</hi> and that when our <hi>Moses</hi>'s are gone, the Spirit which was in those brave men, may be put upon the surviving <hi>Elders of our Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The last thing, that ever our <hi>Eliot</hi> put off, was, <hi>The care of all the Churches,</hi> which with a most Apostolical and Evangelical Temper he was continually solicitous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. When the Churches of <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were under a very uncomfortable prospect, by the advantage which men that sought the Ruine of those Golden and Holy, and Reformed Societies, had obtained against them, God put it into the heart of one well-known in these Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to take a Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> that he might by his Mediations at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> divert the <hi>Storms</hi> that were then impend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over us. 'Tis not easy to express what Affection our Aged <hi>Eliot</hi> prosecuted this undertaking with; and what Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving he rendred unto God for any hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Successes of it. But because one of the last Times, and for ought I know,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49297:84"/> The Last, of his ever setting Pen to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the World, was upon this occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I shall transcribe a short Letter, which was written by the shaking hand, that had heretofore by Writing deserved so well from the Church of God, but was now taking its leave of writing for ever. It was written to the Person that was Engaging for us, and thus it ran;
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>Reverend and Beloved, Mr.</hi> Increase Mather.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>I cannot <hi>write.</hi> Read Neh. 2.10. When <hi>Sanbalat</hi> the <hi>Horonite,</hi> and <hi>Tobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> the Servant, the <hi>Ammonite</hi> heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly, that there was come a Man to seek the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Children of <hi>Israel.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let thy blessed Soul feed full and fat upon <hi>this</hi> and other Scriptures. All other things I leave to other Men; and rest,</p>
                     </q>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Loving Brother, <hi>John Eliot.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>These two or three Lines manifest the <hi>Care of the Churches</hi> which <hi>breath'd</hi> in this great old Man, as long as he had a <hi>Breath</hi> to draw in the World. And since he has left few like him for a comprehensive and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49297:85"/> universal Regard unto the Prosperity<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all the <hi>Flocks</hi> in this Wilderness, we hav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> little now to comfort us in the loss of on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> so like a <hi>Patriarch</hi> among us, but only this; That our poor Churches, it may be hop'd, have still some Interest in the <hi>Cares</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>Who walks in the midst of the Golden Candlesticks.</hi> Lord make our Churches and keep them, yet <hi>Golden Candlesticks!</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>But I have not obtained the end of this History, nor may I let this History come to an end, until I do with some impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity bespeak the Endeavours of good Men every where, to labour in that Harvest which the blessed <hi>ELIOT</hi> justly counted worthy of his utmost Pains and Cares. It was the Confession of <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stocles,</hi> that the Victories of <hi>Miltiades</hi> would not let him sleep in quietness; may those of our <hi>Eliot</hi> raise a like Emulation in those that have now seen the Life of this Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Hero! When one <hi>Robert Baily</hi> many years ago, published a Book, where in several gross Lyes by which the nam<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of that <hi>JOHN COTTON,</hi> who was known to be one of the holiest Men then alive, was most injuriously made odious unto the Churches abroad, were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with some Reflections upon poor
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49297:85"/>
               <hi>New England,</hi> whereof this was one, <hi>The <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y of their Churches hath most exceedingly <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ndred the conversion of the poor</hi> Pagans; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f all that ever crossed the</hi> American <hi>Seas, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hey are noted as most neglectful of the work <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f Conversion.</hi> We have now seen those Aspersions and Calumnies abundantly wip'd away. But let that which has been the <hi>Vindication</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> be also the <hi>Emulation</hi> of the World; for shame, let not poor little <hi>New-England,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e the only Protestant Country that shall do any notable thing for <hi>the Propagation of the Faith,</hi> unto those <hi>dark Corners of the Earth which are full of Cruel Habitations.</hi> But the <hi>Addresses</hi> of so mean a Person as my self, are like to prevail but little abroad with Men of Learning and Figure in the World. However, I shall presume to utter my Wishes in the sight of my Readers; and it is possible that the Great God, <hi>who despises not the Prayer of the Poor,</hi> may by the Influences of his Holy Spirit, upon the Hearts of some whose Eyes are upon these Lines, give a blessed Answer thereunto.</p>
            <p>Wherefore may the People of <hi>New-England,</hi> who have seen so sensible a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Estates of those that
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:49297:86"/> Sell Drink, and of those that Preach Truth, unto the miserable Salvages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, as that even this alone might inspire them, yet from a nobler conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration than that of their own outward prosperity thereby advanced, be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged still to prosecute, first the Civiliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then the Christianizing of the <hi>Barbarians</hi> in their Neighbourhood; and may the <hi>New Englanders</hi> be so far Politick as well as Religious, as particularly to make a Mission of the Gospel unto the mighty Nations of the Western <hi>Indians,</hi> whom the <hi>French</hi> have been of late so studiously, but so unsuccessfully tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with; lest those horrid <hi>Pagans,</hi> who lately (as 'tis credibly affirmed) had such a measure of Devilism and Insolence in them, as to shoot a Volley of great and small shot against the Heavens, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon <hi>the Man in the Heavens,</hi> as they called our Lord, whom they count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Author of the heavy Calamities which newly have distressed them, be found spared by our long suffering Lord, [who then indeed presently tore the Ground asunder, with immediate and horrible Thunders from Heaven round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, but kill'd them not!] for a
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:49297:86"/> scourge to us, that have not used our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to make a vertuous People of them. If a King of the <hi>West-Saxons</hi> long since ascribed all the Disasters on any of their Affairs, to Negligencies in this Point: Methinks the <hi>New-Englanders</hi> may not count it unreasonable in this way to seek their own prosperity. Shall we do what we can that our Lord Jesus may bestow upon <hi>America,</hi> which may more justly be call'd <hi>Columba,</hi> that Salutation, <hi>O my Dove!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May the several Plantations, that live upon the Labours of their <hi>Negroes,</hi> no more be guilty of such a prodigious wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, as to deride, neglect, and oppose all due means of bringing their poor <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes</hi> unto our Lord; but may the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, of whom God will one day require the Souls of the Slaves committed unto them, see to it, that like <hi>Abraham,</hi> they have Catechized Servants; and not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the Almighty God made so many thousands of reasonable Creatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for nothing but only to serve the Lusts of <hi>Epicures,</hi> or the gains of <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monists,</hi> lest the God of Heaven out of meer Pity, if not Justice, unto those un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>Blacks,</hi> be provoked unto a Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:49297:87"/> which may not without horrour be thought upon: <hi>Lord when shall we see</hi> Ethiopians <hi>read thy Scriptures with Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May the <hi>English</hi> Nation do what may be done, that the <hi>Welch</hi> may not be destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>for the lack of Knowledge,</hi> lest our indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to do for their Souls, bring upon us all those Judgments of Heaven, which <hi>Gildas</hi> their Country-man once told them, that they suffered for their disregards un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ours; and may the nefandous Massa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of the <hi>English</hi> by the <hi>Irish,</hi> awaken the <hi>English</hi> to consider, whether they have done enough to reclaim the <hi>Irish</hi> from the Popish Bigottries and Abominations, with which they have been intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>May the several Factories and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, whose Concerns lie in <hi>Asia, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> be perswaded, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> once, and befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him his Grand-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham</hi> was, That they always owe unto God certain Proportions of their Possessions; by the honest payments of which little <hi>Quit-rents,</hi> they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly secure and enlarge their Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Principal; but that they are under a very particular Obligations to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:49297:87"/> Communicate of our <hi>Spiritual things</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those Heathen, by whose <hi>Carnal things</hi> they are enriched: And may they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make it their study, to employ some able and pious Ministers, for the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of those <hi>Infidels</hi> with whom they have to deal, and honourably support such Minsters in that Employment.</p>
            <p>May the poor <hi>Greeks, Armenians, Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites,</hi> and others, in the Eastern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, wearing the name of <hi>Christians,</hi> that have little <hi>Preaching,</hi> and no <hi>Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and few <hi>Bibles,</hi> or good <hi>Books,</hi> now at last be furnished with Bibles, Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Catechisms, and Practical Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises by the Charity of <hi>England;</hi> and may our Presses provide good stores of good Books for them, in their own Tongues, to be scattered among them. Who knows what Convulsions might be hastened upon the whole <hi>Mahomitan</hi> World by such an extensive Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!</p>
            <p>May sufficient Numbers of Great, Wise, Rich, Learned and Godly Men in the Three Kingdoms, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure well-composed Societies, by whose United Counsels the Noble Design of Evangelizing the World, may he
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:49297:88"/> more effectually carried on; and if some generous Persons will of their own accord combine for such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations, who can tell, but like some other Celebrated Societies here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore formed from such small be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, they may soon have that countenance of Authority which may produce very Glorious Effects, and give Opportunity to gather vast Contributions from all well-disposed People, to Assist and Advance this Progress of Christianity. God forbid, that <hi>Popery</hi> should expend upon <hi>Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> more then ten times what we do upon <hi>Saving</hi> the Immortal Souls of Men.</p>
            <p>Lastly, May many Worthy Men, who find their Circumstances will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it, get the Language of some Nations that are not yet brought home to God, and wait upon the Divine Providence, for God's Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to, and Owning them in their Apostolical Undertakings. When they remember what <hi>Ruffinus</hi> relates concerning the Conversion of the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berians;</hi> and what <hi>Socrates,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors relates concerning the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:49297:88"/> Conversson wrought by occasion of <hi>Frumentius</hi> and <hi>Aedesius,</hi> in the <hi>Inner-India,</hi> all as it were by accident, surely 'twill make them try what may be done by design for such things now in our Days! Thus let them see, whither while we at home in the midst of wearisome Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are Angling with Rods, which now and then catch one Soul for our LORD, they shall not be Fishing with Nets, which will bring in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands of those, concerning whom with unspeakable Joy in the Day of the LORD, they may say, <hi>Behold, I, and the Children which GOD has given me!</hi> Let them see, whether, supposing they should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper no farther than to <hi>Preach the Gospel of the Kingdom in all the VVorld, for a VVitness unto all Nations,</hi> yet the End which is then to come, will not bring to them the more happy Lot, wherein they shall stand, that are found so doing.</p>
            <p>Let no Man be discouraged by the Difficulties which the Devil will be ready to clog such Attempts, against
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:49297:89"/> his Kingdom with; for I will take leave so to Translate the Words of the Wise Man, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.4. <hi>VVho is able to stand before ZEAL?</hi> I am well-satisfied, that if Men had the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>To descern the Signs of the Times</hi> they would be all Hands at work to spread the Name of our JESUS into all the Corners of of the Earth. <hi>Grant it, O my GOD; and LORD JESUS come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:89"/>
            <head>BOOKS lately Printed for <hi>J. Dunton,</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>PRoposals</hi> for Printing by way of Subscription, the <hi>Second, Third</hi> and <hi>Fourth</hi> Volumes of the <hi>French</hi> Book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> or History of the Famous Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> which three Volumes, with the first ready publish'd, contain an Account of all the Persecutions that have been in <hi>France</hi> from the beginning of the Reformation, down to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time; comprehending the Reigns of <hi>Henry</hi> III. <hi>Henry</hi> IV. <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. The whole Work faithfully extracted from all the <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Secret Memoirs</hi> that could possibly be procured by that Learned and Judicious Divine Monsieur <hi>Bennoit;</hi> Printed first in <hi>French,</hi> by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Westfriezland,</hi> and now translated into <hi>English,</hi> with her Majesties Royal Privilege. These Proposals are to be had of the Undertaker, <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> and of most Booksellers in <hi>London</hi> and the Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bishop Barlow's Remains;</hi> Containing near an hundred distinct Subjects, <hi>Theological, Philosophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Historical, &amp;c.</hi> in Letters to several Persons of Honour and Quality. To which is added the Resolution of many abstruse Points: As also <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to a Young Divine,</hi> for his study of <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and Choice of his <hi>Library.</hi> Published from his Lordship's Original Papers. Price Bound 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Eleventh Volume of the <hi>Athenian Gazette,</hi> or <hi>Casuistical Mercury,</hi> neatly done up in Marble paper, with a General-Title, Preface and Index
<pb facs="tcp:49297:90"/> to it, (is just now publish'd) resolving all the most <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Curious Questions</hi> proposed by the <hi>Ingenious</hi> of either Sex; from <hi>Tuesday July</hi> 11th to <hi>Saturday October</hi> 21st, 1693. Printed for <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey:</hi> Where is to be had the entire Set of <hi>Athenian Gazettes,</hi> (and the <hi>Supplements</hi> to 'em) for the Year 1691. As also an entire Set for the Year 1692. (or single Volumes to this time.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Young Students Library;</hi> Containing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Abridgments of the most valuable Books printed in <hi>England,</hi> and in the Foreign Journals from the Year 1665. till <hi>May</hi> 1692. To which is added a new <hi>Essay</hi> upon all sorts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by the <hi>Athenian Society:</hi> As also a Discourse concerning the Antiquity, Divine Original and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Points, Vowels and Accents that are plac'd to the <hi>Hebrew-Bible.</hi> The Compleat pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished Monthly, is a Continuation of this Work.</p>
            <p>The First Volume of the <hi>Compleat Library;</hi> Containing an Historical Account of the choicest Books printed in <hi>England,</hi> and in the Foreign Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals for the Months of <hi>May, June, July, August, September, October,</hi> and <hi>November,</hi> 1692. As also <hi>The state of Learning</hi> for those Months; To which is added two Alphebetical Tables; the one of the Books, and the other of the Matters.</p>
            <p>The Second Volume of the <hi>Compleat Library,</hi> for the Months of <hi>December, January, February, March, April, May, June, July, August, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> 1693. Which with the Months of <hi>November</hi> and <hi>December,</hi> (now preparing for the Press) conclude this Second Volume, to which will be added two Alphebetical Tables, the one of the Books, and the other of the Matters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Tragedies of Sin; Together with Remarks on the Life of the Great</hi> Abraham. By <hi>Stephen
<pb facs="tcp:49297:90"/> Jay,</hi> late Rector of <hi>Chiner</hi> in <hi>Oxfordshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liturgia Tigurina;</hi> Or the Book of Common-Prayer, and Administration of the Sacraments, and other Ecclesiastical Rites and Ceremonies usually practised, and solemnly performed in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Chappels of the City and Canton of <hi>Zurick</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and in some other adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as by their Canons and Ecclesiastical Laws they are appointed; and as by the Supream Power of the Right Honourable the Senate of <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> they are authoriz'd, establish'd and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>with the Orders of that Church;</hi> faithfully translated out of the <hi>Helvetian</hi> into the <hi>English</hi> Tongue, by <hi>John Conrad Wernly,</hi> Minister of <hi>Wrasbury cum Langley,</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks;</hi> recommended as a Work that may be of very good Satisfaction and Use, by several of our Reverend Bishops.</p>
            <p>The Tryals of several <hi>Witches,</hi> Lately Executed in <hi>New-England,</hi> with many Remarkable Curiosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therein occurring, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> published by the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Command of his Excellency the Governour of <hi>New-England;</hi> first printed in <hi>Boston,</hi> and now reprinted. The Third Edition.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Further Account of the</hi> New-England <hi>Witches</hi> with the Observations of a Person that was upon the place six or seven days when the suspected Witches were first taken into Examination. To which is added Cases of Conscience, concerning <hi>Witchcraft</hi> and evil Spirits personating men. Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at the request of the Ministers of <hi>New-England,</hi> by <hi>Increase Mather,</hi> President of <hi>Harvard</hi> Colledge. price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> This Book is printed on the same size with the first Account of the <hi>Witch</hi> Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls, that they might bind up together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mensalia Sacra:</hi> Or Meditations on the Lord's Supper; wherein the Nature of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:49297:91"/> is explained, and the most weighty Cases of Consciences about it are resolv'd. By the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Francis Crow,</hi> late Minister of the Gospel at <hi>Clare</hi> in <hi>Suffolk;</hi> to which is prefix'd a Brief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Author's Life and Death, by Mr. <hi>Henry Cuts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Memoirs</hi> of the Right Honourable <hi>Arthur</hi> Earl of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> late Lord Privy-Seal; intermix'd with <hi>Moral, Political</hi> and <hi>Historical</hi> Observations, by way of Discourse, in a Letter: To which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix'd a Letter written by his Lordship, during his Retirement from Court, in the Year 1683. publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sir <hi>Peter Pett,</hi> Knight, Advocate General for the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Conversion of</hi> Theodore John, a late Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er among the <hi>Jews;</hi> together with his Confession of the Christian Faith which he delivered immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before he was baptized. price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Treatise of Fornication,</hi> occasion'd by the late Birth of several <hi>Illegitimates</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave:</hi> To which is added a Penitentiary Sermon, preached before the Guilty Persons, in the publick Congregation, upon <hi>John</hi> 8.11. <hi>Go and sin no more.</hi> By <hi>William Barlow,</hi> Rector of <hi>Chalgrave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Tryals</hi> of <hi>Peter Boss, George Kieth, Thomas Budd</hi> and <hi>William Bradford, Quakers,</hi> for several great Misdemeanors, before a Court of <hi>Quakers,</hi> at the <hi>Sessions</hi> held at <hi>Philadelphia</hi> in <hi>Pensilvania</hi> the 9th. 10th. and 12th. days of <hi>Deoember</hi> 1692. Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing also an account of the most Arbitrary Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of that Court.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Account of the Divisions</hi> amongst the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in <hi>Pensilvania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A further Account of the Divisions</hi> of the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in <hi>Pensilvania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Principles, Doctrines, Laws</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> of the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49297:91"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>